<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dorcas revived the second time: or a sermon preached at the funerals of Mrs. Anne Mickle-thwait the one and twentieth of March 1658.</title>
            <author>Hunter, Josiah, minister in York.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3765B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224179</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834536</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834536</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39037</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39037)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1812:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dorcas revived the second time: or a sermon preached at the funerals of Mrs. Anne Mickle-thwait the one and twentieth of March 1658.</title>
                  <author>Hunter, Josiah, minister in York.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Leach, for Thomas Firby, at Grayes-Inn gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mickle-thwait, Anne, d. 1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39037:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39037:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DORCAS</hi> REVIVED THE SECOND TIME: OR A Sermon preached at the Funerals of M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Anne Mickle-thwait,</hi> the one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of <hi>March</hi> 1658.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOS. HUNTER,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of <hi>Ouſburne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>A gracious Woman retaineth honour, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 11.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Senſus pravae voluntatis mulieribus, non aute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſexus in vitio eſt, <bibl>
                     <hi>Greg. lib. 3. moral. ca. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Leach</hi> for <hi>Thomas Firby, at</hi> Grayes-Inn gate. 1660</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39037:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39037:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Worſhipfull, and my Honoured friends, <hi>John Mickle-thwait</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Joſeph Mickle-thwait</hi> Gent. the Lady <hi>Anna Dickinſon,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Dorothy Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington,</hi> the ſurviving Iſſue of the Worſhipful Mrs. <hi>Anne Mickle-thwait,</hi> late deceaſed.</head>
            <p>IT hath ever been the cuſtom (partly to give, partly to gain reſpect) to commit nothing to the Preſs, but under the inſcription of ſome perſons name, to whom their work might be acceptable, and by whom it might be rendred more acceptable unto others: Now whilſt I thought on the Dedication of the enſuing Sermon, my thoughts never ſtrayed farther, than one of you; to whom, I concluded, that all men; for the argument of it (ſet aſide other reſpects) would adjudge it due, but to which of you, I had none to direct me, and therefore followed mine own fancy, which was this, not to diſ-joyn you, who were ſo nearly joyned in the ſame common relation, and have already approved your ſelves to be the genuine children of the ſame mother: It is not my purpoſe to commend you, but to commend your mother to you, the fruits of your religious edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, do (to the credit of your family and the obſervation of the world) in a great meaſure ſhew themſelves: but let me tell you, you lye under a greater engagement than ordinary: many eyes are upon you, that expect you ſhould bring forth fruit anſwerable to the ſtock that bare you: though you be vertuous, yet you will not be thought worthy of commendation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you excell. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us how he might boaſt, that he was an <hi>Hebrew</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews, 3 Phil. 5.</hi> that is, an <hi>Hebrew</hi> both by the father and the mothers ſide; this it ſeems was eſteemed a great priviledge among the <hi>Jews:</hi> it was deemed a privilege to be a Proſelite, a greater privilege to be an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> but the greateſt priviledge to be an <hi>Hebrew</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew:</hi> ſo may every one of you boaſt, that you are a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> deſcended on both ſides from believing and religious parents, ſuch as did ſo profeſſe themſelves to be, and were accounted really ſo by all that knew them: this is your priviledge, it will be your praiſe, if your practiſe ariſe to the height of it.<note place="margin">Valer. Max. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Romans</hi> forced the lewd ſon of <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> to pluck off from his finger a ſignet-ring, whereon the face of his father was engraven, accounting him unworthy to wear his picture, that would not reſemble his vertue: and if you ſhould degenerate, you will be thought unworthy the name of your parents. This I tell you, not ſo much becauſe I fear you, but becauſe I would not be thought to flatter you: as you have therefore begun well, gone on worthily, ſo continue and abound, knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> have for an example: let the fruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:39037:3"/>
more; that the name of <hi>Mickle-thwait</hi> may be greater, and yield a ſweet and freſh perfume in the Churches of Christ to ſucceedings generations. To this end it is, that I preſent this Sermon to you, deſiring that you would accept of it, and take in good part my freeneſſe with you.</p>
            <p>Now for the Sermon it ſelf, I expect to meet with Cenſures from two ſorts of perſons. They that knew her better than I, will think that I have ſaid too little: and they that knew her not ſo well, will think that I have ſaid too much: In anſwer to the former, I confeſſe I have ſaid too little: When a Painter is about to paint a man, he firſt draweth ſome rude lines and this is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: then he addeth the black colours, this is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: laſtly the vive colours, and this is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now I acknowledge, that toward the reſemblance of your mother, I have only given ſome rude draughts, the moſt that I have done is the adding of black colours: the perfecting of the work which conſiſts in ſuper-adding the vive and lively colours, I leave to a more skilful hand and learned pen, who will lay his foundation lower than I have done, and therefore raiſe his ſuperſtructure higher. For thoſe that think I have ſaid too much, I will only ſay as the Fathers of old to them that doubted of the Trinity, Go with <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Jordan</hi> and there thou ſhalt ſee:<note place="margin">Comitare <hi>Johannem</hi> ad <hi>Jorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debis.</note> ſo go but to <hi>York</hi> and there you ſhall be aſſured; repair to thoſe that were her intimate acquaintance, enquire of them concerning the truth of what I have ſaid, and you will ſay, as the queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> concerning <hi>Solomon,</hi> it is a true report that you have heard of me, yea the half was not told you, <hi>1 Kin. 10.6, 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but one thing more to adde I acknowledge, that I have here and there made add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions and alterations in the Sermon from what I preach'd: and though I had never ſo much time exactly to pen any thing, yet I ſhould alwayes judge it neceſſary before it come to publick view, <hi>lambere foetum,</hi> to look and lick it over again, which when I have done, it will be ſtill unpoliſhed, and my beſt homily nought a kin to <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</hi> Yet if ſome perſons, reputedable enough to judge had not thought it fit to be printed and were earneſt to have it ſo, it had been buried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame walls where is your mothers grave.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord make you to abound more and more in knowledge and in all judgement, that ye may approve things that are excellent, that ye may be ſincere and without offence till the day of Chriſt, being filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe, which are by Jeſus Chriſt unto the glory and prai of God: thus prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 13. 1659</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips obliged and affectionate Servant, <hi>JOSIAH HUNTER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39037:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DORCAS</hi> REVIVED The Second Time.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>9 ACT. 36, 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now there was at <hi>Joppa</hi> a certain Diſciple named <hi>Tabitha,</hi> which by Interpretation is called <hi>Dorcas:</hi> This Woman was full of good Works and Almes-Deeds which She did. And it came to paſſe in thoſe days, that She was Sick and Dyed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE are now met to celebrate the Funerals of a moſt grave and Religious Matron, to whoſe worth (while She was alive) Flattery it ſelf could add nothing; and from whoſe worth (being now Dead) Malice and Envy it ſelf cannot detract any thing. Set aſide the Name of the Perſon mentioned in the Text, and the place of her Habitation, and what the Holy Ghoſt affirms of <hi>Dorcas,</hi> may be as confidently aſſerted of her: She was a Diſciple, full of good Works and Almes-deeds which She did: and it is come to paſſe in theſe days, that She hath been <hi>Sick,</hi> and is now <hi>Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain in them the deſcription of a good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Primitive times, a Woman that excell'd moſt of our Women now, as much as thoſe times for Purity and Integrity excel ours, thoſe times were more Pure and Savouring of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39037:4"/>
ſimplicity than ours, though not ſo pleaſant and delicate, and ſo it is likely were their Women. Concerning her in the Text, you may obſerve 1ſt. her Sex, a VVoman: 2d. her Name, <hi>Tabitha</hi> or <hi>Dorcas:</hi> 3d. the Place of her Reſidence, <hi>Joppa:</hi> 4th. her Profeſſion, a Diſciple: 5th. her Practice, full of good VVorks and Almes-deeds which ſhe did: Laſtly, her Sickneſſe and Death; <hi>And it came to paſſe in thoſe days, that ſhe was Sick and Dyed.</hi> Something of each of theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Her Sex, a Woman. That is obſerved to be true of Women, which is ſpoken of <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> Figs, thoſe that were good, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.25. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.10.</note> thoſe that were evil, very evil, 24 <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. So thoſe Women which we read of in Scripture, that were wicked, were very wicked, as <hi>Jezebel</hi> and <hi>Athaliah:</hi> but thoſe that were good, very good, as <hi>Mary, Anna, Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Dorcas:</hi> &amp; whatever may be <hi>Salomons</hi> meaning, 7 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 28. Yet it is eaſie to obſerve, that the New Teſtament affords good ſtore of good Women; therefore when <hi>Soloman</hi> ſaith, that he had not found one Woman amongſt a thouſand, perhaps he meaneth, not one good VVoman amongſt his thouſand VVives and Concubines that he had. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.3. Or elſe his meaning is, that in reſpect of the diſcovery of Hearts and Natures, whether in good or evil, it is harder to find out throughly the perfect diſpoſition of a VVoman than of a Man: Take his words in the moſt rigorous manner, and all that can be with ſoundneſſe gathered from them is, that good VVomen are rarer than good Men; grant it, yet when they are good, they are (as we ſay) rarely,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Luke</hi> 37. 1 <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 15 <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.16 <hi>Act.</hi> 14.15. 9 <hi>Act.</hi> 39. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. 2 <hi>Epiſt. Joh.</hi> 4.</note> that is, very good, and do equal, if not exceed men. How famous is <hi>Anna</hi> for her Devotion? <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> for her blameleſſe Converſation? the <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> VVoman for her Faith? <hi>Lydia</hi> for her diligent attendance unto the VVord? <hi>Dorcas</hi> for her Charity? <hi>Lois</hi> and <hi>Eunice</hi> for their pious education of <hi>Timothy?</hi> The Elect Lady and her Children for walking in the Truth? And though <hi>Eve</hi> eat that Fruit, which occaſioned the fall of Man-kind, yet <hi>Mary</hi> bare and brought forth that Fruit, which hath raiſed and reſtored Man to a greater happineſſe than he loſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Luk.</hi> 48.</note> and therefore all Generations call her bleſſed. I care not for making Compariſons between Men and Women, ſeeing they are both one in reſpect of Nature, and differ only in Sex; Let thoſe that pleaſe themſelves in playing upon Women, remember that when God created Man, he made them Male and Female,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.</note> and both after his own Image. I will only ſay this, that if God ſend Man to School to Learn of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39037:4"/>
ſuch a deſpicable Creature as the Piſmire 6 <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. Let him not think it any diſparagement to learn ſometimes of a Woman, eſpecially ſuch an eminent and vertuous Woman as <hi>Dorcas: Paul,</hi> the great Preacher of the Gentiles, diſdaineth not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>Priſcilla</hi> one of his helpers in Chriſt Jeſus, 16 <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. And there are writings of Learned Men <hi>extant de illuſtribus Foeminis,</hi> as well as <hi>de illuſtribus Viris.</hi> I will ſhut up this with one word of exhortation to women; for ſhould I not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort women to be as good as they have been, I might be thought to flatter them; I would have you know therefore, that whilſt I commend women that have been good, my purpoſe is not to flatter thoſe that are not good, or at leaſt not ſo good, as the Holy women in old time who truſted in God, and adorned themſelves, not with plaiting of hair, wearing of Gold, &amp; putting on of Apparel ſo much as with the adorning of the hidden man of the Heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet Spirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. I would have women therefore for their encouragement to take notice, that they have as fair Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of their own to write after, as notable Patterns of their own Sex to imitate, as men have; Study therefore to be as Modeſt, Meek, Humble, Obedient, Chaſt, Temperate, Devout, and Charitable, as the Holy women of old time, that you may deſerve ſuch an Honourable Teſtimony, as the Holy Ghoſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth unto <hi>Dorcas.</hi> VVhether <hi>Dorcas</hi> was Maid, VVife, or VVidow, is to us uncertain, nor is it much material to enquire; Labour yee to be full of good works, as ſhe was; and it ſhall be your Honour, and an Honour to your Sex, be your Eſtate what it will. So much of the firſt particular.</p>
            <p>The ſecond follows, and that is her Name; <hi>Tabitha,</hi> which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by interpretation is called <hi>Dorcas. Dorcas</hi> now ſtands in need of interpretation, as <hi>Tabitha</hi> did then. <hi>Tabitha</hi> is a Syriack word, <hi>Dorcas</hi> a Greek word, they both ſignifie in Engliſh, a Roe or Goat. Many Parents (I ſuppoſe) have given their Children, ſince, this name for <hi>Dorcas</hi> ſake; but why <hi>Dorcas</hi> Parents ſhould chooſe to call her ſo, may ſeem ſtrange to us, who are ignorant of the reaſon. However let us not be offended at the name, when we can find no fault with the Perſon: with God there is no reſpect of perſons, much leſſe of names; but if it were before <hi>verbum Soeculi,</hi> it is now become <hi>verbum Eccleſiae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 <hi>Act.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> ſignifies a ſupplanter or deceiver, yet God diſdaineth not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39037:5"/>
to call himſelf the God of <hi>Jacob.</hi> The Perſon if good, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Name be it never ſo mean; and the Name, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good, cannot dignifie the Perſon, if he be evil and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy. <hi>Abel</hi> was a good man, yet his name ſignifies vanity. <hi>Lydia</hi> was a vertuous woman, yet her name ſignifies a ſtanding Pool. <hi>Abſalom</hi> was a traiterous and troubleſome Son, yet his name ſignifies a Father of Peace; and <hi>Michol</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Saul</hi> was none of the beſt women, yet her name ſignifies one who is perfect. To be ſure, it can be no diſparagement to <hi>Dorcas</hi> to be ſo called, ſeeing the Church compareth Chriſt to that thing, which her name imports, <hi>ſcil,</hi> a Roe, 2 <hi>Cant.</hi> 9. And the Roe is commended to us in Scripture for a loving, pleaſant Creature 5 <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. Thus much we may take notice of, that the Lord knoweth every one that belongs to him by name, which he reckons unto <hi>Moſes</hi> as a ſpecial favour 33 <hi>Ex.</hi> 17. And when the famous names of the wicked ſhall rot, the obſcureſt names of his own people ſhall be had in everlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.<note place="margin">10 <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 112. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The place of her Reſidence, <hi>Joppa. Joppa</hi> was a Town ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Sea ſide (Port-Towns have been obſerved to be great inlets to the Goſpel) it was part of the inheritance of the Tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> formerly known by the name of <hi>Japho,</hi> 19 <hi>Joſh.</hi> 46. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 2.16. now it is called by the Inhabitants <hi>Sappho.</hi> VVe find no mention made of <hi>Joppa,</hi> but in this and the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, throughout the whole New Teſtament; and it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, had not <hi>Peter</hi> Sojourned there, and <hi>Dorcas</hi> Lived and Dyed there, that we had not heard of it at all. Now ſo long as <hi>Dorcas</hi> is had in memory, <hi>Ioppa</hi> will not be altogether forgotten. <hi>Of</hi> Zion <hi>it ſhall be ſaid</hi> (in Way of honour) <hi>this and that man was Born there.</hi> 87 Pſal. 5. Good Perſons are an honour to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that they live in, and together with their own names tranſmit the memorial of their Habitations to poſterity. <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem</hi> was but little among the thouſands of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 5 <hi>Mich.</hi> 2. yet it is become famous, becauſe it was the place of Chriſts birth, 2 <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. VVe read how Cities, yea whole Countries have contended for the birth and breeding of famous men. Religious perſons are not only a bleſſing to the places of their abode, whilſt they live; but a credit alſo, after they are dead. As you know, that little Spring amongſt us is become famous, becauſe of that great River of <hi>Ouſe</hi> flowing from it, which is ſo advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Country round about: So many places, though in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39037:5"/>
reſpects obſcure and ignoble, and might have continued ſo without obſervation or remembrance, have become famous, and their memories perpetuated in ſucceeding generations, by the birth or reſidence of ſome honourable perſon. Let us learn from hence to live ſo, that we may not be a diſcredit to the places we live in; There are three things that are the glory of a Country, Arts, Sciences, and Religion; If we deſire to honour the places of our Nativity or abode, we muſt neither be Idle, Ignorant, nor Prophane; if we be, the Earth that we tread on bears us, but we are a burden to it; the Air we breath in, enlivens us, but we are an infection to it.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p>Her profeſſion, a Diſciple. Diſciple was the uſual appellation by which thoſe that profeſſed the truth, were called at the firſt plantation of the Goſpel; at its firſt original, it was appropriated to thoſe who were the ſpecial Attendants of our Saviour, ſo the twelve Apoſtles are called the twelve Diſciples, 10 <hi>Math.</hi> 1. Afterwards as the Church increaſed, ſo the name grew more common; ſo that in Chriſts time they that were frequently his Auditors, are called his Diſciples, 6 <hi>Joh.</hi> 66 and thoſe which afterward were firſt called Chriſtians at <hi>Antioch,</hi> 11 <hi>Act.</hi> 26. were before that time called Diſciples; now this title is given to <hi>Dorcas</hi> 1. <hi>ad Honorem,</hi> 2. <hi>ad Documentum.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Honorem</hi> for Honours ſake. To be a Chriſtian, a Diſciple, a Profeſſour of the Goſpel, is a great honour to any Perſon, to be ſuch an one, not in a large ſenſe as the name of Chriſtian and Profeſſour is now uſed (for it would make a mans heart even abhor and loath to ſee what kind of Profeſſours and Chriſtians we have in our days) but to be ſuch an one in that ſtrict acceptation, that <hi>Dorcas</hi> is entituled here, is a Perſons great honour: Certainly, if holineſſe be the greateſt Honour, and piety the beſt Nobility, then they are to be reputed the moſt Noble and Honourable Perſons, who are Profeſſours of Holineſs, wicked men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves canot gainſay it, when they ſee that the Profeſſion of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is accompanied with the Practice of Piety. How often do we meet with that of <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>Pſalmes?</hi> Lord I am thy Servant, and no doubt but he thought it a greater honour to be the Servant of God than the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> There are three callings in Honour ſtyled Profeſſions, and they are the calling of the Lawyer, the Phyſician, and the Divine; all other callings are accounted leſs noble, Liberal and Ingenuous: but there is a calling and Profeſſion for Nobility beyond all theſe, and that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39037:6"/>
is the calling and profeſſion of Chriſtianity. How have the greateſt Princes and Perſonages on the Earth Gloried in titles of this nature? as the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in being called the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prince; the King of <hi>France</hi> in being ſtyled the moſt Chriſtian King; and our Kings of <hi>England</hi> have thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more famous for the title of Defenders of the Faith. Sure it is, that as there is nothing more honourable than Chriſt and the Goſpel, ſo there is no Profeſſion more honourable than the Profeſſion of the Goſpel and Chriſtianity;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 27.</note> when they that profeſſe the Goſpel have but a care to honour it by walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as becometh the Goſpel: and what though there be ſome Profeſſours, who are vile Perſons, the profeſſion, though leſs honoured, is no leſs honourable. The Miniſtry is a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable calling, though there be many unworthy Miniſters. As ſoon may we think to ſcour the ſpots out of the Moon, as purge the Church of all unworthy Members. Let the ſhame be caſt, where the blame is, there is no ſhame in being a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or in profeſſing to be ſo, but it is a ſhame to profeſs the Goſpel and practice quite contrary to it: indeed the profeſſion of the Goſpel is ſo honourable, that Looſe-Livers, Prophane Perſons, and Hypocrites (if we knew them) are not worthy the name of Profeſſours.</p>
            <p>If then to be Profeſſours be our honour, let us glory in it; and if our profeſſion of the Goſpel ſhall make us vile in the eyes of wicked men,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.21 22.14 <hi>Rev</hi> 1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 9 <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.</note> let us reſolve with <hi>David</hi> in another caſe, I will make yet a greater profeſſion, I will be more vile. They who received the mark of the Lamb, had it in their foreheads a viſible place, to note, that they ſhould not be aſhamed of it. <hi>I will ſpeak of thy teſtimonies before Kings</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) and will not be aſhamed.</hi> 119 Pſal. 46. We live in an age, wherein <hi>Nazianzens</hi> complaint of old may be renewed, nothing is ſo delightfull as the deriding of a Chriſtian; applauſe and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment waits upon them that can <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> rail upon honeſt men in handſome language. <hi>Michol</hi> was barren untill her death,<note place="margin">2 <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 6.23.</note> for ſcoffing at <hi>David</hi> dancing before the Ark; but I know not how (ſaith a learned man) <hi>Michol</hi> is become fruitful, after her death, of a ſcoffing generation. What then? ſhall any that makes profeſſion of the glorious name of Chriſt be afraid of words?<note place="margin">12 <hi>Heb.</hi> 2</note> then may Prophane Perſons ſcoffe indeed: let us rather deſpiſe the ſhame, yea we may glory in this ſhame; the Apoſtles rejoyced, that they were accounted worthy to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39037:6"/>
ſuffer ſhame for his name, 5 <hi>Act.</hi> 41. Oh that ever men, who deſire to be called Chriſtians, ſhould yet be aſhamed to make profeſſion of Chriſtianity, that they ſhould judge that their ſhame, which is their greateſt glory. Let us remember what our Saviour ſaith 8 <hi>Mark</hi> 38. Whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me and my words in this adulterous and ſinfull generation, of him alſo ſhall the Son of man be aſhamed, when he commeth in the Glory of his Father, with the holy Angels. For ſuch of us as have begun to make a more than common profeſſion of the Goſpel, let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering; and let us conſider one another to provoke unto love and unto good works, not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, but exhorting one another, and ſo much the more, as we ſee the day approaching, whether of judgement or of perſecution, as it is, 10 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 23, 2, 4 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorcas</hi> is called a Diſciple here, <hi>ad Documentum,</hi> as for her <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> honour, ſo for our inſtruction. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Diſciple, is as much as a Schollar or Learner, and the Chriſtians in the primitive times were ſo called, becauſe they were brought up at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles feet, and for the acquiring of ſaving knowledge, had their dependance upon the ordinary means of inſtruction, the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or teaching of the word. So then <hi>Dorcas</hi> a Diſcple, that is, as one obſerves, a Schollar in the School of Chriſt, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her ſelf to the Ordinance of God for the ſaving of her Soul; now if Chriſtian and Diſciple be aequivalent and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible terms, then it is eaſy to make the obſervation; That he who is indeed a Chriſtian, is a Learner, one that depends upon, and ſubmits himſelf to the means of inſtruction. To this end were the Scriptures written, namely for our learning 15 <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. and when Chriſt ſent out his Diſciples, he bade them go <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> teach, that is, make Diſciples, 28 <hi>Math.</hi> 19. when Chriſt would ſhew, what mark his ſheep have, He declares it to be an ear-mark, 10 <hi>Joh.</hi> 27. <hi>my ſheep hear my voice;</hi> and therefore are Miniſters of the Goſpel called Teachers, 30 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 20.4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 11. to note, that they who hear them ſhould be Learners. Nor ought any of Chriſts Diſciples to think it a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to be Learners; for if they look at the Perſon of whom they learn, they are Chriſts Miniſters, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 4.1, Chriſts Ambaſſadours, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. they repreſent no meaner a perſon than the Lord of Life and Glory, the great Prophet of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:39037:7"/>
and Saviour of the World: and how meanly ſoever they may be accounted of by men, yet they are called the glory of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. If they look at the things which they learn, they are of an excellent nature, and it will ennoble, elevate and help much to the perfection of their underſtandings: for we ſpeak the wiſdome of God in a myſtery, even the hidden wiſdom, which God ordained before the VVorld unto our Glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. We Preach ſuch things, as the very Angels deſire to look into, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. We Preach Chriſt Crucifyed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. the knowledge of whom is ſo excellent, that <hi>Paul</hi> counted all things but loſſe to gain it. 3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 8. And as we preach concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things of the greateſt excellency, ſo likewiſe of the greateſt advantage, for unto us is committed the Word of Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. So that we are appointed to teach the loſt Children of <hi>Adam</hi> the way to <hi>Paradice</hi> again; how they may, not only make their Peace with God, but be reſtored to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, friendſhip, and familiarity, ſo that they ſhall be admitted to eat of the Tree of Life, and live for evermore. Is it any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement for a man to be a learner of things that are ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and advantagious? Laſtly, let the Diſciples of Chriſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Eſtate, and it is no diſparagement unto them to be learners; for their State is a State of imperfection, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry was ſet up for the perfecting of the Saints. 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 12. When <hi>Eunomius,</hi> that proud Heretick, boaſted how he knew the Divinity, <hi>Baſil</hi> gravelled him in no leſſe than one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty queſtions about the Body of an Aunt, or Piſmire. <hi>Sure it is, a Wiſe Man will hear and increaſe Learning.</hi> 1 Prov 5. <hi>Give in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to a Wiſe Man, and he will be yet Wiſer, teach a Iuſt Man, and he will increaſe in Learning.</hi> 9 Prov. 9. Therefore let none think it a diſgrace to them to ſit in the Learners form, till they be advanced to the Univerſity of Heaven, to have Society with the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>12</hi> Heb. <hi>23.</hi> Si moribundus etiam aliquid didiciſſet. Melch. Adam.</note> 
               <hi>David Chytraens,</hi> when he lay a dying, lift up himſelf to hear the diſcourſes of his Friends, that ſate by him; and ſaid, that he ſhould dye with better chear, if he might dye learning ſomething.</p>
            <p>By this then let us make trial of the truth of our Profeſſion. We do confidently perſwade our ſelves, and profeſſe unto others, that we are the Diſciples of Chriſt, if we be ſo indeed then we are Learners, that is, ſuch as hear inſtruction and grow Wiſe, and refuſe it not, watching dayly at VViſdoms Gates. 8 <hi>Prov.</hi> 33, 34. It is the property of a Learner to be humble, ſenſible
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39037:7"/>
of his ignorance, and ſelf-denying; not proud, ſelf-conceited, or wiſe in his own eyes. The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a ſaying, that he who learneth of himſelf, hath a Fool to his Maſter: and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tells us, that there is more hope of a Fool, than the man that is wiſe in his own conceit. 20 <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. Therefore he that would be wiſe, muſt be a Fool, that he may be wiſe.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note> It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother property of a learner to reverence his teachers; So are we commanded <hi>to know them that Labour amongſt us, and are over us in the Lord, and admoniſh us, and to eſteem them more highly for their works ſake.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.12, 13. Heretofore they have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>the very feet of them beautiful, that brought glad tidings of Peace.</hi> 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. And <hi>Herod</hi> an Hypocrite, did for a time not only rejoyce in hearing <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine,<note place="margin">6 <hi>Mark.</hi> 20.</note> but was alſo very obſervant of his Perſon, Now if theſe be the characteriſtical Notes of a Diſciple, we may juſtly ſuſpect, that as there were many, who ſaid they were Jews, but were not;<note place="margin">3 <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.</note> ſo there are many, who call themſelves Diſciples, that are not ſo indeed, yea that would take it in ſcorn to be thought learners.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Mala.</hi> 7.</note> For though the Prieſts lips preſerve knowledge, and the people ſhould ſeek the Law at his Mouth, becauſe he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſtes; yet generally men are ſo conceited of themſelvs, and have ſuch under-valuing conceits of their Teachers (becauſe their fellow-creatures, and ſubject to like paſſions as they are)<note place="margin">5 <hi>Iam.</hi> 17.</note> that they judge this a very ſervile, and therefore too ſubmiſſe a courſe; This makes me think, as he ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there were more Imitators than true Citizens; ſo that in our days we have more Imitators, than true Chriſtians, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are more ſtrictly ſo taken.</p>
            <p>So I paſſe from <hi>Dorcas</hi> Profeſſion, to her Practice; thoſe two muſt not be ſeperated; for the moſt glorious profeſſion of Religion without good works, is moſt groſſe Hypocriſie, and he that is barren in good works, and yet bears high and broad the ſail of Profeſſion, ſeems to be afraid leſt the World ſhould not take notice of him for an Hypocrite. Good works likewiſe, without a knowledge and profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion,<note place="margin">Splendida pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cain.</note> are no better than glorious Sins, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls them; no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the virtues of Heathens,<note place="margin">Quid vobis (ethnici) cum virtutibus, qui chriſtum dei virtutem igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratis?</note> unto which though we give the name, yet they want the nature of virtue. For as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid, What have you Heathens to do with virtues, who are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of Chriſt, the virtue and power of God unto Salvation? But where a profeſſion of Religion, and a practice of good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39037:8"/>
works are in conjunction, they make <hi>integrum ſanctum,</hi> an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, ſincere, compleat Saint. Such an one was <hi>Dorcas</hi> in thoſe days, ſuch an one was the <hi>Dorcas</hi> of our days. Firſt in general, <hi>Full of good works;</hi> then more particularly, <hi>and Almes-deeds which ſhe did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In general, <hi>She was full of good works.</hi> When it is ſaid that <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of good works, it is not meant, that ſhe was perfect,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.</note> for in many things we offend all; and every Sin is a defect. Much leſſe may we think, that She did works of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errogation; They are ſuper-arrogant, that think themſelves righteous above the Rule; As full as <hi>Dorcas</hi> was, I dare ſay for her bleſſed Soul, that She thought her ſelf empty and barren. Ears that are moſt laden with Corn, hang loweſt down to the ground; and holieſt Perſons have alwayes the humbleſt thoughts of themſelves. Hereby therefore I conceive, are meant three things. 1. She was full of, that is, abundant in good works, as when it is ſaid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 24, 25,</note> that <hi>Jehojada</hi> waxed old, and was full of days, the meaning is, he grew very old: and when it is ſaid of wicked worldly men, that they are full of Children, 17 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. the meaning is, they have many Children: So <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of good works, that is, ſhe was a very good woman, and did abound in good works; To be full of good works, is as much as to be fruitful. <hi>Dorcas</hi> her good works were not few, as the gleaning Grapes,<note place="margin">24 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.</note> when the Vintage is done, or as the ſhaking of an Olive Tree, two or three Berries in the top of the uttermoſt bough, four or five in the moſt fruitful branches thereof;<note place="margin">17 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5,</note> but ſhe was full of good works, like the Vine before it is gathered, and the Olive Tree before it be ſhaken. 2. She was full of good works, that is, She did not only abound, but in ſome ſort ſuper-abound, conſidering her condition: She did very many good works, even beyond the expectation of thoſe that knew her, when they compared what She did, as they imagined with what She had: they would not have thought, that She had ſo rich a Treaſury, that would have furniſhed her to expend ſo liberally. They could not but think, that her ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of good works abroad, would bring her to want at home: Yet ſo it was, She did many good works; nor did they draw her dry, but ſome way or other She was ſupplyed, that She ſtill did more; it is very probable that <hi>Dorcas</hi> was not a woman of great worldly Eſtate, and if ſhe had not been notable for her good works, She might in other reſpects have lived obſcurely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39037:8"/>
enough: But whatever her eſtate was She had a free heart, and did not for fear of wanting her ſelf, hold back her hand from ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the neceſſities of others. The Widow that caſt her two Mites into the Treaſury, is ſaid to have caſt in more than they that caſt in greater gifts,<note place="margin">21, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1, 2, 3.</note> becauſe what they gave was out of their abundance; but ſhe caſt in all that ſhe had. So <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of good works, that is, She did abound, yea ſhe did ſuper-abound comparing her abilities with her expence, She did more than ſhe was ſuppoſed able to do, 3. She was full of good works, that is, her works were not only abounding, but abiding; She did not ſatisfie her ſelf with what good ſhe had done,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 13.11 <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.</note> but ſtill ſhe did more; with the Apoſtle ſhe forgot that which was behind; and though ſhee had done very much good, yet ſtill ſhe with-held not her hand; according to the injunction 6 <hi>Gal.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>Let us not be weary in wel-doing, for in due ſeaſon we ſhall reap, if we faint not, as we have therefore opportunity, let us do good.</hi> Out of the good Treaſure of her heart, She was ſtill bringing forth good things.<note place="margin">12 <hi>Math.</hi> 35</note> She was like the Orange-tree, of which they write, that it is bringing forth fruit all the year long as ſome are ripe, ſo others are ſtill budding: And as it is ſaid of the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.</note> her works were more at the laſt, than at the firſt. Hereby She made it appear that ſhe was no Hypocrite, who is moved by an external principle, and doth his good works only for particular ends, and therefore continues not always to do good: But She was a ſincere Chriſtian whoſe good works flowed from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Principle of grace, and were directed to an univerſal end, Gods glory. So then <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of good works, that is, She did very much good, more than could be expected from ſuch a Woman, and thus ſhe continued to her death;<note place="margin">24 <hi>Mat.</hi> 46.</note> and ſo was one of thoſe bleſſed ſervants, whom her Lord, when he came, ſound well-doing.</p>
            <p>Good works are ſometime ſtrictly taken for works of Charity becauſe that Love is the fullfilling of the Law,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>10.</hi> de civ. Dei ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; hac ſibi Deus vel pro ſacrificiis, vel prae ſacrificiis placere teſtatur,</hi> God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of works of Charity for ſacrifices, with ſuch ſacrifices God is well-pleaſed, 13 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 16. Yea he accepts them before ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> 9 <hi>Math.</hi> 13. But often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times good works are taken more largely for the whole obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a Chriſtian, ſo we are ſaid to be Gods workman-ſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works. Sure it is,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Eph.</hi> 10.</note> the Law is the Rule of good works and therefore obedience to any branch<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39037:9"/>
of the Law is a good work; as the breach of any part of the Law is an evil work; and as the <hi>Logicians</hi> ſay, there is no created be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but it is reduced into one of the ten predicaments; ſo there is no duty or good work commanded of us, but it is contained in one of thoſe ten words,<note place="margin">10 <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.</note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> calls them, that is Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Theſe good works in other places of Scripture are called good Fruits, 3 <hi>Jam.</hi> 17. Fruits of righteouſneſſe, 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 11. Fruits of the Spirit, 5 <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. Fruits worthy of Repentance, 3 <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. and amongſt many other expreſſions, they are called armour of light, 13 <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. Good works therefore are of a very large extent; yet it hath pleaſed the Holy-Ghoſt, to reduce them under three heads, 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 12. Sobriety towards our ſelves, Honeſty towards our neighbour, and Godlineſs towards God. So that when it is ſaid, <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of good works, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is this, She was very Sober, Honeſt and Godly in reſpect of her diſpoſition; and full of Acts of ſobriety, honeſty and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in her converſation.</p>
            <p>Only take notice of this, before I come to the Doctrine. Though <hi>Dorcas</hi> be here commended for her good works, yet the Scripture ſpeaketh ſometimes of good works by way of Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution and debaſing of them; which in what reſpect it is done, is very neceſſary for us to obſerve. Take notice therefore, when good works are compared with the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, in relation to juſtification, then they are rejected as unable for any ſuch uſe, and called menſtruous rags, 64 <hi>Iſ.</hi> 6. droſs and dung, 3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 8. when the beſt works we do, are conſidered in the Court of Juſtification, there they are damnable and have ſo much droſs in them, that God doth reject them as who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſufficient: but look on them as fruits of Faith, done out of obedience to Gods command, and with reſpect to his Glory, and ſo the Scripture doth highly commend them. Thus then the Scripture commends good works againſt the Antinomian, who holds them unneceſſary: but condemns good works, yea the beſt works, againſt the Papiſt, who holds them to be meritorious whereas when we have done all,<note place="margin">Niſi Deus per miſericordiam pareret; non haberet quos per juſtitiam coronaret, in Pſ. <hi>100.</hi>
               </note> we muſt ſay that we are unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and acknowledge with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that unleſs God did ſpare in mercy, he ſhould find none, whom he might Crown in juſtice; ſurely he that relyes upon his works, doth like a man that on a moon-ſhinie night miſtakes his own ſhadow for a bridge, and ſo falls into the River and is drowned.</p>
            <p>Now let the obſervation be this; All that make profeſſion of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39037:9"/>
the Goſpel ſhould accompany their profeſſion with fruitfullneſs in good works, So <hi>Paul</hi> gave in charge to <hi>Titus, Theſe things I will that thou affirm conſtantly, that they which have beleeved in God be carefull to maintain good works</hi> 3 <hi>Tit.</hi> 8. two greek words are obſervable <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that it be their care and ſtudy, the bent of their minds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to maintain, or rather to be examples and preſidents, going before others in good works; theſe are the richeſt and moſt uſuall ſtyles of commendation in Scripture. <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man mighty in words and deeds. <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 10 <hi>Act</hi> 2. 7 <hi>Luk</hi> 4.5. 9 <hi>Act.</hi> 39. 16 <hi>Rom.</hi> 23. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16.</note> a man fearing God and giving much Alms. The <hi>Centurion</hi> worthy of favour, for He hath built us a Synagogue. <hi>Dorcas</hi> made ſo many Coats for the poor. <hi>Gaius,</hi> the Hoſt of the Church. <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> hath <hi>Paul</hi> his earneſt Prayers for mercy, becauſe he often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed him; and as one obſerves wittily, the Scripture ſpeaks but little of the learning of the Apoſtles, but much of their Acts.</p>
            <p>The reaſons why Profeſſours of the Goſpel ſhould be full of good works are theſe, 1 becauſe true Chriſtian Religion doth not conſiſt meerly in Negatives. It is not ſufficient to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from evil, except we do good; ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, 1 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. <hi>That Tree which bears not good Fruit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13 <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>is a Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berer of the ground, and ſhall be cut down for the Fire; as well as that which boars ill fruit and poyſons the ground.</hi> We muſt not only put off Wrath, Malice, Blaſphemy,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> filthy Communication and Lying, but put on alſo bowels of Mercie, Kindneſſe, Humbleneſſe of mind, Meekneſſe, Long-ſuffering, and above all Charity, which is the bond of Perfection.<note place="margin">18 <hi>Luk</hi> 11.</note> Thou ſayſt that thou art no Extortioner, unjuſt, or Adulterer; but this is not ſufficient; thou telleſt of the evil works which thou doſt not; but where are the good works thou doſt? though he be uſually accounted a good man, that doth no evil; yet he is rather an evil man (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) that doth no good. And we read that at the day of Judgement men ſhall be condemned, not only for the evil that they have done,<note place="margin">25 <hi>Matth.</hi>
               </note> but for the good that they have left undone. Many there are that ſeem to be Religious, when they deceive their own hearts; For pure Religion and undefiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and the Father is this, to viſit the Father-leſſe and the Widow, and to keep our ſelves unſpotted from the world.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jam.</hi> 27.</note> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we give teſtimony of the truth of our Profeſſion, when we are fruitfull in good works; For he that profeſſeth himſelf to be a Chriſtian and is barren in good works, is like a painted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39037:10"/>
Tree, that ſtands only for ſhew; like <hi>Zeuxes</hi> Vine, painted ſo lively, that the Birds came to pick at it, thinking to have fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their bellies, but went away hungry, as they came: or like the Fig-tree in the Goſpel, of which Chriſt thought to have eaten,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>21</hi> Mat. <hi>18, 19.</hi> Ruffin. Eccleſ. Hist. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> but when he came near, it had nothing but leaves; as one <hi>Moſes</hi> renowned for piety, ſaid to <hi>Lucius</hi> reputed an <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhop, tendring the confeſſion of his Faith to clear himſelf; Tuſh ſaith he, what telleſt thou me of the Faith of the Ears? let me have the Faith of the Hands: So thou telleſt me, that thou art a conſtant hearer of the word, thou art able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe out of it; but (Oh man) what telleſt thou me of the Faith of the Ears, or the Faith of the Tongue? let me ſee the Faith of the Hands; Few (I confeſſe) troubled with the deaf and dumb Spirits in theſe times,<note place="margin">Ubi bona opera non apparent ad extra, ibi fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des non eſt ad intra. Mr. Burgeſſe.</note> but moſt having withered Hands. It was a ſaying of <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> that where good works are not without, there Faith is not within; and ſo ſome learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men ſay, that good works are neceſſary to preſerve a man in the State of Juſtification, though they do not immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr to the Act: as in a man, although his Shoulders and Breaſt do not immediately concurr to the Act of Seeing, yet if a mans Eyes and Head were not knit to thoſe parts, he could not ſee; and though the Fire do not burn, as it is light, yet it could not burn, unleſſe it were ſo. The chief ſcope of St. <hi>Iames</hi> his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, is to urge hearers to be doers, and vain boaſters of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith, to juſtifie their Faith by their works.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God is gloryfied by good works; therefore ſaith our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, 5 Mat. 16. <hi>Let your light ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and gloryfie your Father, which is in Heaven.</hi> The men,<note place="margin">31 <hi>Job</hi> 20. 29 <hi>Job</hi> 15. 1 <hi>Jam.</hi> 25.</note> for whom our Heavenly Father is Gloryfied, are ſuch whoſe works ſhine before men, who warm the Loins of the Poor, and by their knowledge are an Eye to the blind. For ſuch men God is bleſſed of men, and ſuch men ſhall be bleſſed of God in their Deeds. The Sun it ſelf, if it did not ſhine, and give warmth unto the Creatures, were the glorious Face thereof ten times more glorious than it is, none would half ſo much bleſſe God for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Good works were one end of Chriſts death. 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 14. there the Apoſtle ſaith, that Chriſt dyed, to purchaſe unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works, not only fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers but zealous; and leſt men ſhould think, that we ſhould only preach free-grace, theſe things ſpeak (ſaith he) and exhort.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39037:10"/>
So it is ſaid, that he ſuffered for Sin,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21</note> leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps: <hi>Now he went about doing good.</hi> 10 Act. 38. <hi>And himſelf bare our Sins in his own body on the Tree, that we being dead unto Sin, ſhould live unto righteouſneſſe.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Good works are an ornament to our profeſſion.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 27. 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> When we are full of good works, we walk as becommeth the Goſpel, and adorn the Doctrine of God and our Saviour. A Chriſtian, though, like <hi>Leah,</hi> tender-ey'd, and cannot ſee farr into the myſteries of Religion, yet if fruitful, is more honourable than barren <hi>Rachel,</hi> though fair and beautiful for parts and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; The credit of the Goſpel ſhould be dear to the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of it, and woe to him who maketh that worthy name, by which he is named, to be evil ſpoken off.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Jam.</hi> 7.</note> Hence flows ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Good works being an honour to our profeſſion, they will put to ſhame, and ſilence prophane perſons,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</note> who are ready to take all occaſions to Blaſpheme; yea through our good conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, we may be inſtrumental for the gaining of thoſe that are without. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls good works, unanſwerable ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes, invincible demonſtrations, to confute and convert Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then if this be our Doctrine;<note place="margin">Appl.</note> it is manifeſt that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do moſt falſly charge us to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, deſpiſers, yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demners of good works. We condemn them in no other ſenſe than the Scripture condemnes them, otherwiſe we commend them as the beſt ſigns of a living Faith, and the expreſſions of thankfulneſſe to God for redeeming us by his Son. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we think <hi>Urſine</hi> hath very fitly entituled his tractate of good works <hi>de gratitudine.</hi> We ſay that God commands good works, is well pleaſed with them, and glorified by them, and though they cannot merit eternal life (for that is the gift of God) yet there is in them an ordinability to eternal life,<note place="margin">6 <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 23.</note> which is not in evil works; And they do render the Subject capable of Heaven, whereas evil works do wholly unfit him. Therefore we are ever preſſing upon our Auditors, to learn to maintain good works for neceſſary uſes, that they be not unfruitful, 3 <hi>Tit.</hi> 14. And we teach them, that good works are neceſſary in a fourfold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. 1. <hi>Neceſſitate praecepti,</hi> by the neceſſity of precept; this is the will of God. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. 2. <hi>Neceſſitate ordinis,</hi> by the neceſſity of an inviolable order, whereby a rational Creature is obliged to yield all obedience to his Creator. 3. <hi>Neceſſitate
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39037:11"/>
conſequentiae,</hi> by a neceſſity of conſequence, becauſe good works do flow from the very eſſence and being of Faith. Laſtly, <hi>Neceſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſive hypotheſeos,</hi> by a neceſſity of the means, or a conditional neceſſity; for though no man can be ſaved for his works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet without good works he ſhall not be ſaved; for if yee live after the fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 6 <hi>Galat.</hi> 7.</note> yee ſhall dye: and whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap: therefore good works are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Bernard, Via ad regnum,</hi> though not <hi>cauſa regnandi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It reproves ſuch, as make profeſſion of the Goſpel, and yet inſtead of being full of good works, are full of evil works; concerning whom it may be ſaid,<note place="margin">32 <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</note> that their Vine is the Vine of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and of the fields of <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> their Grapes are Grapes of Gall, their cluſters are bitter. Their works are works of the fleſh, Adultery, Fornication, Uncleanneſſe, Laſciviouſneſs, Idolatry,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Gal.</hi> 19.</note> Witchcraft, Hatred, Variance, Emulations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, Envyings, Murders, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, and ſuch like; Of ſome one, or more of theſe they are full. Theſe men are the ſcandal of the Goſpel, and by how much Chriſtian Religion is the beſt of Religions, by ſo much are theſe the worſt of men; and no man ſo vile in the eyes of God,<note place="margin">10 <hi>Luk.</hi> 33.</note> and Men, as a debauched Chriſtian, he doth not only bring ſhame,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Joh.</hi> 22.</note> but alſo ſuſpicion upon his profeſſion; for howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Samaritan, not the Jew, relieved the diſtreſſed Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller; yet the Jews Religion was true, not the Samaritans; So in other caſes, truth of cauſes muſt not be judged by Acts of Perſons: Yet as he ſaid, it muſt needs be good that <hi>Nero</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes, ſo many are ready to ſay, it cannot be good, ſurely it cannot but be evil, that ſuch a wicked wretch profeſſeth. What ſhall I ſay to ſuch? do yee think it enough to ſay, that you have <hi>Abraham</hi> to your Father?<note place="margin">3 <hi>Mat.</hi> 9, 10.</note> Will you Steal, Murder, commit Adultry, Swear falſly, and come and ſtand before God in the Houſe called by his name,<note place="margin">7 <hi>Jer,</hi> 9, 10. 8 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſay, we are delivered to do all theſe abominations? ſhall I tell you, that yee are of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Devil, and his works you doe? take it how you will, the Scripture ſaith expreſly, that the Devil worketh in Children of Diſobedience,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</note> ſuch as thou art. Or Laſtly, Shall I tell thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that for ſuch works, comes the wrath of God upon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Diſobedience.<note place="margin">5 <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.</note> Thou art full of evill work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, God is full of patience, that doth not as yet pour out of the Vials of his wrath upon thee, but take heed, what thou doſt, God is preſt under thee as a Cart,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Am.</hi> 3.</note> that is full of ſheavs; if the Axeltree of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39037:11"/>
his Patience break, the burthen will fall on thee, a burthen ſo heavy,<note place="margin">6 <hi>Rev.</hi> 57.</note> that thou wouldſt be glad to change it for Rocks and Mountains.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us all be exhorted, in this to make <hi>Dorcas</hi> our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern. She was neither Idle, Evil, nor Unfruitful; Not Idle, for we read of her works: nor Evil, for her works were good: nor Unfruitful, for ſhe was full of them. 1. <hi>Dorcas</hi> was not Idle,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.13.</note> for we read of her works. She was none of thoſe women, that learn to be idle, and wander about from Houſe to Houſe. Good works (ſaith <hi>Gerrhard</hi>) in Scripture are taken,<note place="margin">In Loc. Com.</note> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for external actions, but for inward affections to good; but it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to uſe the name of works, rather than habits or affections, becauſe the praiſe of true virtue conſiſts in action. Sure it is, man was made for action: and though ſome Sciences, in compariſon of others more opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, are termed ſpeculative; yet not one of them, whoſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation tends not to, and ends in ſome operation, whereby man is advantaged, and God honoured; ſpecially Divinity, which is, <hi>ſcientia affectiva &amp; effectiva.</hi> We loſe the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all our ſpeculations, reading and diſcourſing about Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, if we reduce them not into good works; It is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of practice, which makes the ſtudy of the Law ſo ſweet; and that is accounted the beſt paſture, which is ſeen in the fleſh and fleece of the Sheep. To little purpoſe it is, that we do <hi>excolere animum,</hi> Till and ſow our minds with the Seeds of good notions, if theſe Seeds bring not forth fruit in our works and actions. The bleſſing of <hi>Daniels</hi> pulſe and water,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Dan.</hi> 15.</note> was ſeen in the fatneſſe and well-favouredneſſe of his countenance: So the bleſſing, that God gives to all our Meditating, Reading, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Diſcourſing, is ſeen by our fruitfulneſſe of good works. What is a man the better for the Seed he ſoweth, if it rot in the ground, or bring not forth a crop, that will reward him for his labour? If a mans Meat be ſweet, and doth not nouriſh him, it is a ſign of an ill digeſtion; and thy notions are raw, indigeſted notions, if they turn not into actions and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And as we loſe the ſweetneſſe, ſo others loſe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of our ſpeculations, if not converted into good works; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an idle perſon is not unfitly compared to the dumb jack in a Virginal, whilſt the other dance out a ſweet and winning Muſick, it diſturbs the whole body with an ill-diſtemper'd la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zineſſe. 2. <hi>Dorcas</hi> was not Evil, for her works were good.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39037:12"/>
One might better be idle, than not well-employed, for to be ſure,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15.</note> his work ſhall be burnt, if he be not burnt for his work: ſo that he is ſure every way to receive loſſe; and he that is not imployed in doing a good work, ſuffers a double loſſe, both <hi>propter lucrum ceſſans &amp; propter damnum emergens:</hi> For whilſt a man hath been doing evil, he might have been doing ſome good, which would have proved an advantage to him, therefore in that reſpect he ſuffers loſſe; but he hath been doing evil, which will prove unto him evil, and here is a double loſſe. Now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Conſtitution of a good work, many things are required; eſpecially theſe four, a right Rule, a right Motive, a right Principle, a right End.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A right Rule, that is, the Law of God. As the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer can draw no good line, which is not commenſurate to the Rule; So neither is any work thou doſt, good (though never ſo ſpecious) if not conformable to the Word. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the Commandements of men.</hi> 15 <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. The blind whelps of will, worſhip, and ignorant devotion, God regards not. Counterfeit Coin is ſo farr from being currant, that the Coining of it is a capital Crime; and all works which have not the ſtamp of Gods word upon them, are ſo farr from being acceptable, that they are abominable to him; and he rejects them with a, <hi>who hath required theſe things at your hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.</note>2. A right Motive; Unto a good work it is requiſite that we do not only what is commanded; but that we do it <hi>ex intuitu voluntatis,</hi> becauſe it is commanded. In all good works, there muſt be not only a knowledge of, but a reſpect to the will of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. 12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 5 <hi>Eph.</hi> 17. 7 <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 4 <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 18 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 31.</note> which is therefore uſed ſo frequently, as an argument to enforce our obedience, becauſe we ought to do every thing in conſcience to Gods command: For to do that which God wils, and not to do it, becauſe he wils it, is not obedience, and therefore not a good work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A right Principle, and that is a good heart. Do men ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Grapes of Thorns, or Figs of Thiſtles? a corrupt Tree can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth good fruit. Such as the Fountain is, ſuch are the Streams. Therefore we are commanded to waſh our Hearts; to make unto our ſelves new Hearts; becauſe we muſt be good, before we can do good. When the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> promiſed, that they would do all that God had commanded them by <hi>Moſes;</hi> What ſaith God, <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an Heart in them,</hi> 5
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39037:12"/>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. It is not for thee to promiſe, that thou wilt lead a new life, endeavour to be full of good works;<note place="margin">11 <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Oh labour to get ſuch an Heart in the. By nature wee are wild Olives, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt by Humiliation be cut off from our own Stocks, and by Faith put into Chriſt, and ſo the property of the ground of our Hearts alter'd and meliorated,<note place="margin">8 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> ere we can bring forth good Fruit. Therefore we affirm, that an unregenerate man cannot do a good work; for they that are in the fleſh,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.13.</note> cannot pleaſe God; and wickedneſſe will proceed from the wicked.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A right end, and that is Gods glory; whereunto all our Actions muſt be referred, or elſe ſeem they never ſo good,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</note> they are no better than Phariſaical. Therefore the Apoſtle prays, that the <hi>Philippians</hi> might be fill'd with Fruits of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to the glory and praiſe of God, 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 11. It is the mark,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 11.</note> that directs the eye; Therefore where a mans mark is not good, his aim is nought, and ſo is his Action. No Creature, we ſay, was made by it ſelf; and therefore not made for it ſelf, but him that made it: So there is no good work, which we can do of our ſelves, therefore we ought not to do it for our ſelves; but for his praiſe, from whom we have the power.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</note> And I make no queſtion, but ſo farr as a man is convinced, that what good he doth is from God, and not himſelf, ſo farr will he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, the good that he doth unto God and not to himſelf. Therefore a true Chriſtian aſcribes the glory of his good works to God, as the Author; and directs his good works to the glory of God, as his end.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Dorcas</hi> was not unfruitful, for ſhe was full of good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> works. This was the praiſe of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that they were full of goodneſſe, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. of <hi>Stephen,</hi> that he was full of Faith and power, 6 <hi>Act.</hi> 8. and of <hi>Barnabas,</hi> that he was a good man, and full of the Holy-Ghoſt, and of Faith, 11 <hi>Act.</hi> 24. This was their praiſe, and will be ours if we be ſuch, or in truth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be ſo: Yet this is a ſmall thing in compariſon of the Glory, that ſhall redound to God (for what is our praiſe to Gods glory) now herein (ſaith our Lord) is my Father glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, that ye bear much Fruit, 15 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. A Chriſtian in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is compared to a Vine; and a Vine brings forth Fruit by Gluſters, not here and there a Grape, but cluſters of Grapes: Beloved, you all profeſſe your ſelves to be engrafted into Chriſt, I tell you, it is a diſhonour to the Root, on which you profeſſe your ſelves to grow, to bear ſuch unprofitable branches.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39037:13"/>
A garden encloſed is my Siſter, my Spouſe, thy Plants are an Orchard of Pomgranates with pleaſant fruits, Camphire with Spikenard, Spikenard and Saffron, Calamus and Cinamon, with all Trees of Frank-Incenſe, Mirrhe and Aloes, with all the chief Spices; thus Chriſt ſets out his Church 4 <hi>Cant.</hi> 13. She was a Garden full of all the varieties of the heavenly Trees and flowers of Grace. And it may be ſaid of every Tree of this Garden, as of the teeth of Chriſt 4 <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. they are like a flock of ſheep even ſhorn, which come up from the waſhing, whereof every one beareth twins and none is barren amongſt them. It is a great ſhame for any of us not to be fruitfull, whom God hath planted in a ſoil ſo fruitfull of all things pertaining both to Life and Godlineſſe. But our barrenneſs in good works may juſtly provoke God to turn our fruitfull Land into barrenneſſe;<note place="margin">107 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 2. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 21 <hi>Math.</hi> 41.</note> and not only take away his own Corn and his Wine and his Oyl, his Wool and his Flax from us, but even the Goſpel it ſelf and give it to a Nation that will bring forth the fruits of it. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially I have it in charge from the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 17. 9 <hi>Jud.</hi> 8.</note> to charge ſuch as are rich in this world, to be rich in good works. I read, that when the Olive and Vine and Fig-tree were invited to be Kings over the reſt of the Trees; they pretended, that they would not leave their Fatneſs, and Sweetneſs, and Fruitfulneſs for promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as though a man could not bear fruit and bear Rule toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. God forbid, that any of you ſhould make your riches or greatneſs an excuſe for your barrenneſs in good works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But it was intended only as a Parable by him, that ſpake it; and ſo I leave it.</p>
            <p>I paſſe from <hi>Dorcas</hi> commendation in the general, to that thing for which ſhe is eſpecially commended to our imitation, which is that ſhee was full of almſ-deeds, which ſhe did. By alms-deeds are meant works of mercy to thoſe that are in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. Now works of mercy reſpect either Soul or Body; thoſe which reſpect the Soul are ſix; uſually comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this verſe, <hi>Inſtrue, Caſtiga, Remitte, Solare, Fer, Ora,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, Reprove, Forgive, Comfort, Suſtain, and Pray. They which reſpect the Body are likewiſe ſix, contained in another verſe, <hi>Viſito, Poto, Cibo, Recolligo Veſtio, Condo,</hi> Viſit the Sick, Refreſh the Thirſty, Feed the Hungry, Redeem the Captive, Cloath the Naked, and Burie the Dead. Now thoſe works of mercy which reſpect the Soul, are of the two the better Alms-deeds; therefore for certain <hi>Dorcas</hi> did not omit them; though
<pb facs="tcp:39037:13"/>
elſe I think that by Alms-deeds in the Text, are chiefly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood works of mercy reſpecting the Body.<note place="margin">Obſerv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Profeſſours of the Goſpel ought to be very charitable to the Poor, <hi>I have not eaten my morſels alone</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job) I have ſeen none to periſh for want of Cloathing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">31 <hi>Job.</hi> 17. 19 <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 10 <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>Philem. v</hi> 7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1 16. 16 <hi>Rom.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>the loins of the Poor have bleſſed me, becauſe he was warmed with the fleece of my ſheep.</hi> To paſſe by the example of <hi>Zacheas, Cornelius, Philemon, Oneſipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Gaius</hi> and others; the example of Chriſt is moſt notable, who though he lived by contribution himſelf, yet gave out a ſhare to the poor, and had his Almoner to that purpoſe, 13 <hi>Joh.</hi> 29. though this be a common Doctrine, yet becauſe it is not commonly practiſed, it will not be unneceſſary to adde a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or two to enforce it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Diſtributing to the neceſſities of the poor, is a work which God doth ſtricktly enjoyn. Amongſt many places I will ſelect two; one out of the Old Teſtament 15 <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.8. <hi>If one of thy brethren with thee be poor, thou ſhalt not harden thine heart nor ſhut thy hand from thy poor brother, but thou ſhalt open thine hand wide unto him.</hi> The other is out of the New Teſtament 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6.17. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, laying up in ſtore for themſelvs a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life.</hi> Hearken then (my Bretheren) it is not left arbitrary to you,<note place="margin">Biſhop Hall in a Serm. on <hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>6.17</hi>
               </note> that you may do good if you will; but it is laid upon you as your charge and duty, and woe be to you, if ye do it not, Do good, if ever ye look to receive good. If ever ye look to be rich in Heaven, be rich in good works upon the Earth. There muſt be a <hi>Date,</hi> ere there can be a <hi>Dabitur;</hi> Give and it ſhall be given.<note place="margin">19 <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>He that gives to the poor, lends to the Lord, who payes large encreaſe for all he bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows: but how ſhall he give you the intereſt of Glory, where he hath not received the principall of beneficence?</hi> As the <hi>Graecian</hi> ſaid of very tall men, that they were <hi>Cypreſs</hi> Trees, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fair and tall but fruitleſs; So may I ſay of ſtrait-handed rich-men; and theſe <hi>Cypreſſes</hi> are not for the garden of Paradice; none ſhall ever be planted there but the fruitfull. If the firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice had any Trees in it, only for pleaſure; I am ſure the ſecond, which is in the midſt of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22 <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.</note> ſhall have no Tree that bears not twelve Fruits; yea whoſe very leaves are not beneficial.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Give me leave to ask you this queſtion: if you knew what
<pb facs="tcp:39037:14"/>
to offer unto God, that might be pleaſing and acceptable to him, would ye not do it?<note place="margin">43 <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.</note> are ye not glad, that ye have any thing wherewith to preſent a great man (whoſe favour you need) that he delights in and will accept of? and methinks, you ſhould be glad, that you have any thing, wherewith you may do a work that is pleaſing to the Majeſty of Heaven and Earth. Well mind that of the Apoſtle, 13 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 16. <hi>To do good and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi> the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> God is delighted or more properly (as he obſerves in his Critickes) <hi>hilariter affectus,</hi> cheerfully affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch ſacrifices. Beloved, I beſeech you, conſider; ſhall not we poor men, we ſinfull men, who are worms and no men, between whom and God there is ſuch an infinite diſtance as cannot be expreſſed, ſhall not we rejoyce from our hearts, that we can do any thing, which may be acceptable and well-pleaſing to God, which may delight and give complacency to him? you ſee, what will pleaſe him. Oh be not ſo backward to do that which God is ſo forward to accept of: be not ſo unkind as to withhold that from God, which he is ſo ready to take as ſo great a kindneſſe from you.<note place="margin">22 <hi>Job.</hi> 2.3.</note> The Lord ſtands not in need of any of your gifts, yet he is pleaſed with your ingenuity: you cannot be profitable to the Almighty, but you may be pleaſing to him; and what is there you can deſire more than acceptance with God and Chriſt, who tels you, that whatever ye do to the leaſt of his Brethren, he takes it as done unto himſelf, 25 <hi>Math.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. 14 <hi>Math.</hi>
               </note>Laſtly conſider, that by giving you ſhall gain; as the bread broken in the Goſpel, multiplyed. Ask and have is the rule of Prayer; but give and have is the rule of Liberality. He hath diſperſed, he hath given to the poor, His horn ſhall be exalted with honour, 112 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. He ſhall have a <hi>Cornu-Copia</hi> of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, Riches, and Honour too, to boote: and his Arms ſhall be an horn effundent in a barren Field.<note place="margin">Miſeros pro pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia, miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes pro be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolentia.</note> That ſaying of <hi>Leo</hi> is worthy our obſervation; the Divine juſtice and wiſdom (ſaith he) ſuffers many to labour under great miſeries, that he might crown the miſerable for their patience, and the mercifull for their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence. <hi>Paul</hi> compares giving of Alms to the ſowing of Corn,<note place="margin">Ad ſemi nantis potius quàm ad ſuſcipientis lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra cedit. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nbr.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. now as ſowing Corn turns more to the benefit of him, that ſoweth it, than of the Earth that receiveth the Seed; ſo in giving of Almes, the advantage is more to the Giver than the Receiver. This is one advantage you ſee: The times we live in are times of great ſickneſs and viſitation now
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39037:14"/>
God hath promiſed, that he will have a ſpecial care over ſuch, as are mercifull to the poor, 41 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. Bleſſed is he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth the poor, the Lord will ſtrengthen him upon the bed of languiſhing, thou wilt make all his bed in his ſickneſſe, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not how ſoon it may be thy lot, to be viſited with ſickneſſe: If thou conſidereſt the condition of thy poor Brethren in diſtreſs, thou art ſure to have carefull attendance, honourable attendance, not only an attendance of Angels, but God himſelf; he will make thy bed and ſtrengthen thee upon thy bed. This Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is a great Priviledge, and thou canſt not believe it and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate in this caſe. Again, hereby thou ſhalt convey a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Poſterity, 37 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. he is ever mercifull and lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and his ſeed is bleſsed. Thirdly, this is a means to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Eſtates to you; 11 <hi>Luk.</hi> 41. give Almes of ſuch things as ye have, and behold all things are clean unto you. But Laſtly,<note place="margin">19 <hi>Math.</hi> 29.</note> what is all this to that hundredfold, which you ſhall receive in the life to come? when you ſhall for the bread that ye have dealt to the hungry, be fed everlaſtlngly with heavenly Manna, Angels food: for the water wherewith you have refreſhed the Thirſty, drink of the Well of life for evermore: For the Garments wherewith you have covered the naked, walk with the Lamb in white: and for every pecuniary act of charity, receive a Crown and a kingdom glorious, incorruptible, and that fadeth not away.<note place="margin">Appl.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Be pleaſed likewiſe to receive this Doctrine with all readineſs of mind.<note place="margin">8 <hi>Amos</hi> 11.</note> I cannot but complain of a great Famine and Dearth of Alms-deeds, though (bleſſed be God) we have neither a Famine of Bread nor of hearing the Words of the Lord. What ſhould be the reaſon of it, I know not, it is becauſe men are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of Poperie and dare not give much, leſt they ſhould be thought ambitious to merit thereby? No, No; the reaſon is, becauſe the pride and private luxury of our days are ſuch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4</hi> Jam. <hi>2.3.</hi> Auro parietes, auro laquearia, auro fulgent capita columna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; nudus atque eſuriens ante fores no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras Chriſtus in paupere mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Hieron. ad Gaudeat.</note> that they cannot maintain theſe but with the ſtarving of Charity: this makes men that they are ever coveting, and yet ſo far from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that they never have enough: Like unto Kites and Gleads that are ever watching and catching for prey, and yet remain Carrion-lean, becauſe converting the greateſt part of of their nouriſhment into long feathers. We ſee it is ordinary for walls to be cloathed and men to go naked, yea as <hi>Jerome</hi> complaind, Walls and Pillars of Houſes ſhining with Gold, and Chriſt in a poor man ready to dye, naked and hungry before the doors. Oh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39037:15"/>
ſurely, much of this might be ſpared and given to the Poor; but ſo it is come to paſs, that the lean Kine have devoured the fat and it cannot be known (but by their pride) that they have eaten them up.<note place="margin">41 <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.20 21.</note> This makes the Papiſts to call us Soliſidians; and gives occaſion to others, to break ſuch jeſts on the heads of men eminent in the Church, as he did upon the Jeſuits (whom in forain Nations they call Apoſtles) the Apoſtles indeed ſhewed the World Heaven, left the Earth to Earthly men and got Heaven themſelves: but we are more beholding to our new ones, For they ſhew us Heaven, leave it to us to purchaſe, in the mean time ſeeking only for themſelves earthly poſſeſſions. I beſeech you therefore, as yee tender the credit of your Profeſſion, that you would make more conſcience of this duty, as ye abound in Faith, in Utterance and Knowledg; ſee that ye abound in this grace alſo, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. and remember the words of our Lord Jeſus how he ſaid, it is more bleſſed to give than to receive. You cannot ſay,<note place="margin">20 <hi>Act.</hi> 35.</note> (as they 25 <hi>Math.</hi>) When ſaw we any hungry or athirſt, or ſtrangers, or naked, or ſick, or in Priſon, and did not miniſter unto them? you either ſee or hear of ſuch every day; the world is an Hoſpital full of them, why then do ye not miniſter unto them <hi>Bernard</hi> ſhall tell you;<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>21</hi> ſup. Cantic.</note> ask a covetous rich man, what he thinks of thoſe, that laying out what they have for Gods glory and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of thoſe that are in neceſſity, do thereby purchaſe unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the rich merchandiſe of heaven with their earthly ſubſtance whether they do wiſely or no?<note place="margin">Procul dubiò reſpondehit, ſapienter.</note> without doubt he will ſay, that they do wiſely. Ask him again, why he himſelf doth not that, which he ſo well approves of in another?<note place="margin">Profectò domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na avaritia non permittit.</note> I cannot, will he ſay, why? Madam Covetouſneſs (or Madam Pride) will not ſuffer me. But remember that he ſhall have judgment without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that hath ſhewed no mercy, 2 <hi>Jam.</hi> 13. whereof we have an example in <hi>Dives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">16 <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </note> who becauſe he would not give <hi>Lazarus</hi> a crum on Earth to alay his hunger, was denyed a drop in Hell to quench his own thirſt.</p>
            <p>But whilſt I am ſtirring you up to this duty, I may not forget to give you ſome directions in the practice of it. 1. The Alms which you give, give them freely. This is the rule, Let him that ſheweth mercy, do it with cheerfulneſſe 12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. For God loveth a cheerfull Giver 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. if your Alms are extorted from you, they cannot be called benevolence, becauſe not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with good will. I know not well what to call it, but give it what name you will, I am ſure it is not acceptable to God.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39037:15"/>
For the will is ſo greatly concernd in this buſineſſe, that where there is not ability, God accepts it for the deed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12 therefore whatſoever ye do, do it heartily, as unto the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 23.</note> let thy fountains flow forth (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) 5 <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. To note how free we ſhould be in works of this nature, that our Alms ſhould come from us like water out of a Fountain, and not like water out of a Still, that is forced by Fire. And to ſhew this Freeneſſe, we ſhould not always ſtay till we be asked, but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Poor and ſo take a courſe to releive their modeſty,<note place="margin">41 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.</note> as well as their neceſſity. For there are many needfull, that yet are unwilling to ask. We ſhould not expect, but prevent the crying of the Poor. God Forbid, the Heavens ſhould not rain, till the Earth firſt open her mouth; For there is ſome ground, that will ſooner burn then chap.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What Alms you give, give them with compaſſion.<note place="margin">Aliud eſt dare indigenti, aliud affectum miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiae cum indigente par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri. <hi>Anſalm.</hi>
               </note> So we are commanded to remember them that are in Bonds, as bound with them, 13 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3. This is called a drawing out of the Soul to the hungry, 58 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. It is one thing to give our goods, another thing to give our affection. He that gives his goods to the Poor, gives that which he is without himſelf, but he that gives compaſſion, gives part of himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What Alms you give, give diſcreetly. I think, I need not adviſe any to give more than he is able; For every one will be carefull enough to look to that. And indeed it is a mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo to help to light his neighbours candle, that he do not put out his own. Surely none need be more bountifull in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, than the Sun is in ſhining, which though freely beſtowing his beams on the World, keeps notwithſtanding the body of light to himſelf. But we ſhould be diſcreet in judging of the perſons, to whom we give.<note place="margin">Paeuperes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</note> Some have ranked the Poor into three ſorts. Firſt Gods poor, or Chriſts poor, ſuch as have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered loſs of Eſtate for Chriſt, or being otherwiſe fallen into po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty make profeſſion of the Goſpel. Secondly,<note place="margin">Pauperes mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. Pauperes Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli.</note> the Worlds Poor; ſuch as have deſcended from poor Parents and ſo live in a poor eſtate. Thirdly, the Devils poor; ſuch as have Riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly waſted their ſubſtance, whatever it was, more or leſs; that by wickedneſs have conſumed their Eſtates, and after they are conſumed, do yet continue in their wickedneſs being notoriouſly vicious and debauched. Now certainly we are to have pitty on all theſe, but not all alike. Chriſts poor are moſt to be pittyed, the Worlds poor next, the Divels poor leaſt of all. Yet they muſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39037:16"/>
not be wholly neglected, but as we would do all good offices to their Souls, ſo we muſt not deny the doing of neceſſary offices to their bodies. Do good to all, but eſpecially to the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith.<note place="margin">6 <hi>Gal.</hi> 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. What Alms you give, give them in ſimplicity, 12, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Not like the Hipocrite, that bloweth a trumpet before his Alms, that he may have glory of men. Our left hand muſt not know what our right hand doth 6 <hi>Math.</hi> 3. upon which ſome have commented thus,<note place="margin">Vid. Maldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</note> let not thy left hand, that is, thy wife, know what thy right hand, that is, thy ſelf doth. Others thus, let not thy left hand, that is, thy moſt familiar Friend, know what thy right hand,<note place="margin">Qui laudem hominis intu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens dedit, ſibi non pauperi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit aut ſiquid dedit vendidit non donarit.</note> that is, thy ſelf doth. But the ſcope of our Saviour is plain, which is to warn us againſt Hipocriſie and vain-glory in giving Alms, For as <hi>Maldonate</hi> well obſerves upon the place; He who gives Alms to get the praiſe of men gives them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and not to the poor; or if he give any thing, he hath rather ſold than given it: The poor could not pay him for his Alms, but others do it for him; For whilſt they only behold him that receives, they commend him that gives, <hi>et praetium eſt illi vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri:</hi> It is a reward to him to be ſeen to give. Therefore <hi>Jerome</hi> taxed a noble Roman Dame,<note place="margin">Vt Religio ſior videretur.</note> who being at St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, there with her own hands gave peices of mony to the poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that ſhe might ſeem to be more religious. This ſaith <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Nepotian,</hi> is rather to be called an hunting after praiſe,<note place="margin">Venatio magis quam eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na dicenda.</note> than a giving of Alms in ſimplicity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What Alms we give, let us give them ſeaſonably. Let us not put them off till our death. In the morning ſow thy ſeed, (begin ſoon) and then hold on: In the Evening with-hold not thine hand,<note place="margin">Poenitentia vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra nun quam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, ſed rarò vera, ſi ſera.</note> 11 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6. I do not condemn Funeral beneficence, but I prefer the other; and I think the ſame may be ſaid of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, that is uſually ſaid of Repentance; true liberality is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver too late, but late liberality is ſeldom true. He that gives not till he dyes, ſhews that he would not give, if he could keep it longer. That which men give thus (ſaith Biſhop Hall) they give it by their Teſtament, but I can ſcarce ſay, that they give it by their Will.<note place="margin">112 <hi>Pſ.</hi>
               </note> The good mans praiſe is, <hi>Diſperſit,</hi> he hath diſperſed his goods, and not left them behind him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mr. Hieron on the Text.</note>I read lately an Embleme of Charity comprehending all or moſt of theſe directions. A child with a merry countenance, covered in a cloud, with a bloody heart in his hand, giving ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39037:16"/>
to a Bee without wings. Firſt a child, to note that we ſhould begin this work early: looking merrily, to note, that we ſhould do it cheerfully: covered in a cloud, to note, that we ſhould do what we can, to hide our Liberality: with a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy heart in the hand, to note, with what ſenſible compaſſion we ſhould do it: Laſtly, giving honey to a Bee without wings, to a Bee, not a Drone that will not work; and to a Bee without wings, that cannot work; to note, that we ſhould give diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not to the Loyterer, but to the Labourer, whom God hath diſabled from working. So much of <hi>Dorcas</hi> practice, She was full of good works in the General, and likewiſe of Alms-Deeds in Particular; As Mr. <hi>Hieron</hi> calleth her, a diſcreet, compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, cheerfull and Simple-hearted Almoner. I come now to the ſad part of my Text, and that is her ſickneſs and death. It may be, you have heard me hitherto with delight; if I now ſtirr up your grief, I cannot avoid it; But I muſt go, as I am led by the Text and the occaſion. Who would not be ready to ſay, it was pity that <hi>Dorcas,</hi> ſo good a Woman ſhould all any thing, that ſhe ſhould be ſick, but much more, that ſhe ſhould die? But ſo it ſeemed good to Divine Providence. For it came to paſſe in thoſe days, that ſhe was ſick and died.</p>
            <p>And it came to paſſe.<note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> There is a providence in and to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Sickneſſe and Death of Gods Saints. Pretious in the ſight of the Lord,<note place="margin">116 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> is the Life and alſo the Death of his Saints: And if they be ſo pretious to God, how can we think, but that there ſhould be a ſpecial providence in their Sickneſſe and Death? If the hairs of their Heads are numbred,<note place="margin">10 <hi>Mat.</hi> 30.</note> much more the days of their Sojourning; and if one of their hairs cannot fall to the ground, but by the providence of their Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, much leſſe can their whole bodies. There is a threefold Providence of God; Firſt, General, which he exerciſeth over all his Creatures; Secondly, Special, which he exerciſeth over Man; Thirdly, Particular, which he exerciſeth over his own People. Of this laſt the Pſalmeſt ſpeaks, 56 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. Thou telleſt my wandrings, put thou my Tears into thy Bottle, are they not all in thy Book; God in his providence orders the time, when his people ſhall be ſick and Dye; the place where; the Diſeaſe of which; with all other circumſtances of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and which is above all, he doth faſhion their Hearts by the ſame providence to bear Sickneſſe, and ſo diſpoſeth of things, that they are not taken away by Death, till they have
<pb facs="tcp:39037:17"/>
finiſhed their work, and are fit to enter into Glory. Well then, let us ſee his providence, and ſubmit to it, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Juſtice, Wiſdom, and Goodneſſe of it. We are apt oft times to wonder, that God ſhould caſt his people into Sickneſſe, and take them away by Death at ſuch a time, that he caſteth them into ſuch places (it may be) where they are at a diſtance from their Habitation, that they are taken away by ſuch a ſharp Diſeaſe and violently, that he doth not ſpare them a little to recover their ſtrength, before they go hence; and be no more ſeen.<note place="margin">39 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.</note> Now we muſt anſwer all ſuch queſtions as theſe, with a <hi>ſic evenit,</hi> ſo it came to paſſe by the moſt wiſe providence of God, whoſe reſpect to his Children is ſuch, that if he had ſeen any thing better, this had not been.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note>
               <hi>It came to paſſe in thoſe days, that She was Sick.</hi> Gods deareſt Children are not exempted from Sickneſſe, no more than any other affliction,<note place="margin">Si amatur, quomodo infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur.</note> it is ſaid, 11 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. Behold, he whom thou loveſt is Sick, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> asks, if he were beloved, how came he to be Sick? But in outward accidents of this life, God makes no difference; Nay it is uſual in providence, that they who have Gods Heart,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> feel Gods Hand moſt heavy. It is a very pretty ſaying of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> Gods Children are not neer him, unleſſe they be within the reach of his Rod. They ſit, as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſaid he did, when he ſate between <hi>Virgil</hi> and <hi>Horace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inter ſuſpicia &amp; lachrymas.</note> (the one melancholly, the other troubled with ſore eyes) between ſighing and weeping. All the day long have I been plagued and chaſtned every Morning ſaith <hi>David,</hi> 73 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. When yet it is ſaid of ſome wicked worldly Men,<note place="margin">73 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.</note> that they were not in trouble like other Men, neither were they plagued like other Men. You have read (it may be or heard the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the holy <hi>Hermite,</hi> that having lived to a compleat Age, (though very piouſly) yet made a queſtion of Gods love to him, becauſe all that while he had not (which he could remember) felt one hours ſickneſſe: It pleaſed God in ſome ſhort time, before he dyed to viſit him with an Ague, which he bleſſed God for,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and received as a Love-token, not ſcrupling that ſo much afterward, which formerly had troubled him. <hi>Paul</hi> had a racking pain, which he expreſſeth by a Thorn in the fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Mr. Manton.</note> A learned Man thinks that he alludes to ſuch kind of puniſhment, as Slaves, or Men not free, were put to for great offences. They ſharpned a Stake, and pointed it with Iron, and put it in at his Back, till it came out at his Mouth, and ſo with
<pb facs="tcp:39037:17"/>
his Face upward he Dyed miſerably: And therefore by that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, the Apoſtle intendeth ſome grievous bodily diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or racking pain.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Coo.</hi> 12.5.</note> Certainly he ſpeaketh of ſuch an infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherein he would Glory; and therefore it is not probable, that it ſhould be meant of Sin, or ſome prevailing Luſt, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expound it; but rather of ſome extreme corporal pain. Yet I have obſerved, that Gods Children are not apt to queſtion his Love, ſo much, as in Sickneſſe. For <hi>Satan</hi> takes the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the ſolitude of a Sick perſon, to tempt him more: and makes uſe of the pain and diſtemper of the Body, to diſturb and diſquiet the mind. But however Gods people have no more cauſe to doubt of Gods love in Sickneſſe, than any other affliction. That which troubles them moſt is, that hereby they are rendred unſerviceable; but where God diſenableth from du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he looks not for it, but accepts of the deſire for the deed. Beſides, Sickneſſe it not ſuch an unſerviceable Eſtate; may not one ſerve God acceptably in ſuffring, as well as doing? As it is ſaid in the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14 <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.</note> here now is the Faith and Patience of the Saints. Therefore if God ſhall caſt your Bodies into Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, be not dejected, caſt not down your Spirits.<note place="margin">38 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 7 <hi>Job.</hi> 3, 4. 38 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 27.</note> Gods deareſt Saints have had experience of ſore Sickneſſes, ſuch as <hi>Hezekiah, Job, David,</hi> and <hi>Epaphroditus.</hi> The Children of God have Bodies of the ſame matter and making with other men. They are but earthen veſſels, ſubject to knocks and cracks as others are; only they have a more pretious Lamp ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in theſe earthen pitchers, than others have, I mean a more pretious Soul. Therefore comfort your ſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in Sickneſs, all your deſire is before God, and your groaning is not hid from him, 38 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. And though your bodily diſtemper indiſpoſe you for duty, yet God accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> prayer, 38 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. though when he prayed, he did but chatter like as a Crane or a Swallow. 38 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. So much of <hi>Dorcas</hi> Sickneſs.</p>
            <p>I come now to her Death. It is very probable, that <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi> had been Sick before, but not unto Death, but now <hi>She was Sick and Dyed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I will not break forth into any Rhetorical Declamations againſt the cruelty of Death, yet the Scripture calls it an Enemy, and the laſt Enemy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and it doth the worſt it can, even to Gods own people; But it may be ſaid of it, as <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid of his Enemies, they may kill me, but they cannot hurt me. For what <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid of Martyrdome,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is true
<pb facs="tcp:39037:18"/>
of any kind of Death to Gods Children; it is but a way to paſſe from a Temporal Life to an Eternal. <hi>She Dyed.</hi> The Holyeſt and moſt Religious perſons are ſubject to Death. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the <hi>Patriarches,</hi> theſe all Dyed (ſaith he) 11 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Grace gives comfort in Death, but not power againſt it. It is one of the Statutes of Heaven, which cannot be revoked. <hi>Statutum eſt</hi> 9 <hi>Heb.</hi> 27. it is appointed for all Men once to die. There is no man hath power over the Spirit to retain the Spirit, neither hath he power in the day of death, and there is no diſcharge in that Warr, 8 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8. no union unſeperable, but that between Chriſt and a believer. Death will ſeperate the union between Husband and Wife, between Children and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> yea the union between Soul and Body for a time;<note place="margin">Privilegia ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularia regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam non faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, regulam non infringunt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Perſonalis Actio moritur cum perſona, nec ſunt ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anda privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legia.</note> but not the union between Chriſt and the Soul: for when the people of God are diſſolved, then they go to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all. If it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> never ſaw Death; the Anſwer is, that ſingular privileges neither make a Rule, nor break a Rule; theſe were perſonal privileges, and a perſonal Action ever dies with the perſon; Neither are privileges to be amplified, for then they are no privileges. Though Chriſt hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſting of Death that it cannot hurt us; the ſtrength of Death that it cannot always hold us; yet hath he not as yet, altogether deſtroyed it: But the beſt men muſt dye, that as Sin brought in Death, ſo Death may again caſt out Sin. Death was firſt inflicted as the puniſhment of Sin, now it is the end of it.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.</note> Therefore do the holyeſt men dye, that their mortality may be ſwallowed up of life. Again, ſometimes God takes away his deareſt Children by Death,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.</note> as he did <hi>Joſiah</hi> from the evil to come. Laſtly, that of the Apoſtle is conſiderable, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Martyrs he ſaith, of whom the World was not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. 11 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 38. The World is apt to deride, revile, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne, and caſt aſperſions upon good men; they will not profit by their Admonitions and good Examples; therefore the World is worthy no longer of their Societie, and God takes them away; He thinks, that he hath let them live but too long, to have no kinder uſage, and therefore he takes them up <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſpeaks, to their heavenly kindred where they ſhall be more made of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 4.</note>Hence we learn, that as they are Fools, who account the Godly mans life madneſs; ſo are they that think their end to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39037:18"/>
be without honour. It is not the miſery of good men that they die. For he is not miſerable, that dyeth but once and for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that death may for ever be ſwallowed up of life: But he is miſerable, that is ever dying and yet lives in torments infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſe then death: Thus it is with the wicked in Hell, who paſſing out of this life are immediately ſeiſed on by the ſecond death. but for the Godly, the Scripture ſaith, bleſſed and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is he that hath part in the firſt Reſurrection, on ſuch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death ſhall have no power, but they ſhall be Preiſts of God and of Chriſt. Secondly, the Godly are deſirous of death;<note place="margin">20 <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Phil</hi> 23.</note> for love is an affection of Union; Now Chriſt is with the Saint here, there is ſecurity in that; but the Saint alſo would be with Chriſt, for in that there is full foelicity. Laſtly, though the holieſt Perſons die, yet God ſuffers not Death to put in his Sickle before they be ripe. There is no queſtion, what age ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Dorcas</hi> was of, being ſo full of good works, She could not but be fit for Heaven. For this reaſon a Chriſtian can never die out of ſeaſon. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that he was as one born out of ſeaſon,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8</note> becauſe he had not ſeen Chriſt on Earth; but he could not die out of ſeaſon, becauſe he was ſure to ſee Chriſt in Heaven.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Dorcas</hi> died, the Text tells us? but how ſhe died, it doth not tell us, neither was it very neceſſary, for we may be confident, that She who lived ſo piouſly, could not but die peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably. She that was ſo full of good works in her life, we may probably think, that ſhe was not full of fears at her death. The wiſe man tels us, that the wicked is driven away in his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, but the righteous hath hope in his death. 14 <hi>Prov.</hi> 32, <hi>Dorcas</hi> being ſo righteous a woman, could not but have hope in her death, and it is very probable, She had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>The full aſſurance of hope,</hi> 6 <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. It is likely, She had that full aſſurance of hope, that filled her with joy; But to be ſure, She had that hope in her death,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Rom</hi> 5.</note> which would not make her aſhamed at the day of Judgement.</p>
            <p>I will only add this, now <hi>Dorcas</hi> is gone, her works we are ſure have followed her long ſince; and our praiſes can add no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to her glory, only they are an excitement to our ſelves. To him that ſoweth righteouſneſſe there ſhall be a ſure reward, 11 <hi>Pro.</hi> 18. Which reward <hi>Dorcas</hi> now hath. For God is not unrighteous, that he ſhould forget <hi>Dorcas</hi> works and labour of love, which She ſhewed towards his name, in that She miniſtred
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39037:19"/>
unto the Saints, 6 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. That <hi>Dorcas</hi> Soul is bleſsed I can tell you; But how bleſſed, if I had the tongue of Men and Angels, I could not tell you. The Scripture hath left us but a Negative deſcription of the Saints bleſſedneſs, Eye hath not ſeen nor Ear heard &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Paul</hi> was tranſlated out of himſelf to behold it,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor</hi> 12.</note> and being returned into himſelf could not expreſs it. Doe not envy <hi>Dorcas</hi> her happineſs, but imitate her holineſſe.<note place="margin">14 <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. 25 <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note> She hath reſted from her labours and received her Crown; but left us ſtill to ſweat and toil in Gods Vine-yard; Nor muſt we think to come to Heaven upon eaſier terms than Gods Saints have done before us; Wherefore let us gird up the loyns of our minds, let us every day be adding more Oil to our Lamps, that an entrance may be miniſtred unto us abundantly, into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is time now that I haſten to a concluſion. I have ſpoken what I intend, of <hi>Dorcas</hi> in the Text. Let us now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Give me leave to parallel the <hi>Dorcas</hi> that is dead in our days,<note place="margin">27 <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.</note> with the <hi>Dorcas</hi> that was ſick and dyed in thoſe days: And ſurely in water, face cannot anſwer to face more adaequately, than her converſation that is now dead, did anſwer to <hi>Dorcas</hi> whilſt ſhe was alive. But before I fall on this, I beg leave to enter two Pleas in this Holy Court: The one on the behalf of others, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the behalf of my ſelf. Firſt, I profeſs, that I was not deſired, either directly or obliquely by the Perſon deceaſed or any of her Relations, or other to ſpeak any thing of her, Alas, it needed not;<note place="margin">11 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 31 <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.</note> for though dead, ſhe yet ſpeaketh; and her own good works, whereof ſhe was full, were ſufficient to praiſe her in the Gates. The ſecond Plea I enter on the behalf of my ſelf and that is this, if I had been deſired yet I ſhould not have ſaid any thing of her, had I not known her my ſelf and took it for granted that many others knew her to be a perſon exemplary for Piety, and ſo worthy to be commended as a pattern for our imitation. Therefore what I do in an extraordinary caſe, I do not intend to bring into an ordinary uſe, or encourage others to do it. And now having put in theſe two Pleas, I ſet my ſelf to the work. I know,<note place="margin">Ne immittas pecus tuum in pratum, ubi non eſt ſepes.</note> I have matter enough, if not more than I can Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally diſpoſe. But I remember the councel of the Proverb; Put not thy Cattel into a paſture, where there is no hedg. Therefore I will bound my ſelf within the limits of the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, it is ſaid of <hi>Dorcas</hi> that ſhe was a Diſciple; ſo was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39037:19"/>
the Gentlewoman deceaſed, and as it is ſaid of <hi>Maason,</hi> not only a Diſciple, but an old Diſciple, 21 <hi>Act.</hi> 16. and her Age rendred her Diſciple-ſhip the more Honourable; for the hoary Head is a Crown of Glory, if it be found in the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, 16 <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. hoarineſs is then honourable,<note place="margin">Canities tunc venerabilis eſt, quando ea gerit, quae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiem decent. Chryſ.</note> when it doth ſuch things, as becomes ſuch an Age. So did ſhe behave her ſelf, as <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Titus</hi> direct the Aged Woman, 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. She was in behaviour as becommeth Holineſs, and a teacher of good things. Her converſation was a dayly Sermon to the young women about her; Now when I ſay, that ſhe was a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, my meaning is (as in the entrance I explained it) firſt that ſhe was a profeſſour of the Goſpel, and this ſhe was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of, but accounted her glory, and therefore would not diſſemble her profeſſion in any place, or amongſt any company. She was not like thoſe effoeminate women, <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks of, who were <hi>pudoris magis ne mores quàm ſalutis;</hi> And though ſhe did not (as ſhe did not expect to) eſcape the ſcoffings and reproaches of wicked perſons, yet being conſcious to her ſelf of nothing, whereof they might accuſe her, having the witneſs of a good Conſcience, ſhe accounted her accuſations,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>..</note> her glory; and thought that they did but (according to the Attick phraſe) waſh her fairer with ſuch aſperſions.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I have often obſerved it in her, how ſhe deſpiſed the ſhame, which attended the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>She was a Diſciple, that is, a Learner; one that had her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> upon the ordinary means of inſtruction. She was not like thoſe, that having got a little knowledg by the Miniſtery, come to be puffed up, and afterwards contemn it; herein deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us, as Mules do with their Dams, having ſucked our Milk, they kick us with their heels. She was farr from the fancie of perfection, either in knowledge or grace; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſhe ſenſible of the neceſſity of the means.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2, 3.</note> She was converted by the Miniſtery of the word, and ſo ſhe deſired the ſincere Milk of it, to grow thereby, having once taſted how gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious the Lord is. The Miniſtery ſhe allwayes looked on as a Divine calling, and the ordinance of preaching as the means,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 11, 12, 13.</note> whereby God would gather in and build up the Saints till the comming of Chriſt; and though ſhe had attained to a great meaſure both of underſtanding and holineſs more than ordinary, and had her aboad in a place, where ſhe enjoyed the beſt helps to increaſe them, yet ſhe deſpiſed not the weakeſt means. Two
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39037:20"/>
Two things there were indeed, which ſhe diſliked; that men ſhould take upon them the Miniſtery as a calling, who had not a lawful calling to it.<note place="margin">5 <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.</note> The other was, that very young experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced men ſhould take upon them this weighty Office: She thought them like young Children, that would be feeding and ſerving themſelvs, before they knew with what hand to do it, or were able to diſtinguiſh between the right hand and the left; So do they take on them, to feed not only themſelves, but others, not only with Milk,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Heb.</hi> 14.</note> but ſtrong Meat, before they have their Sences exerciſed to put a difference between the right hand and the left, between Truth and Errour. She was ſenſible, what advantage ſuch Preachers give to Papiſts and Sectaries: and therefore it was a deſire of the credit of the Miniſtery, together with the ſucceſſe of it, that made her wholly to diſlike the one, and in a great meaſure to diſlike the other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of good works, ſo was this our <hi>Dorcas.</hi> Good works are two-fold, either <hi>inhoerent</hi> wrought in us, or <hi>tranſient</hi> wrought by us. She was full of both; Firſt, of good works inhoerent wrought in her, that is, of the graces of the Spirit.<note place="margin">45 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.</note> Like the Kings Daughter, all glorious within. And her adorning was chiefly of the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible; for after this manner in the old time,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4, 5.</note> the holy women alſo, who truſted in God, adorned themſelves. She accounted Gods Image her greateſt bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and glory:<note place="margin">3 <hi>Rom.</hi> 23.</note> grace was her Jewel, and her Soul was a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet full of ſuch Jewels. The firſt means of her converſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grace (I have heard her ſometimes ſay) was the miniſtery of one Mr. <hi>Rhodes,</hi> a painful Preacher, who at that time lived in or not farr diſtant from <hi>Hull.</hi> Before that time, ſhe would ſay, ſhe was very vain, ignorant and inconſiderate: and yet, it may be, her vanity then was as good, as that which paſſeth for great grace among many now, I mean ſtrict civility: but being once ſpiritually illuminated, with <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhe accounted that which the World eſteems precious, to be but droſſe and dung in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the excellency of the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt her Lord.<note place="margin">3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 7, 8.</note> More particularly.</p>
            <p>She was full of the Grace of Faith; and therefore notably well acquainted with the promiſes,<note place="margin">Pabulum fidei.</note> which are the food of Faith: A diligent attender on the word,<note place="margin">Organum fidei. <hi>10</hi> Rom. <hi>17.</hi> Nutrimentum fidei.</note> the inſtrument of Faith: An earneſt deſirer, and a moſt conſcientious frequenter of the Lords Supper, the means to increaſe it: and by reading the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39037:20"/>
hearing the Word, receiving the Sacrament, joyned with a ſpecial Act of application in them all, ſhe had attained to a kind of Plerophorie, a full aſſurance of Faith.<note place="margin">10 <hi>Heb.</hi> 22.</note> When ſhe was now Sick, ſhe told me that ſince her converſion, ſhe had at ſeveral times many doubts and fears ariſing in her Heart, <hi>Satan</hi> deſired to Winnow her as Wheat, but (ſaid ſhe) my Faith failed not. God did enable her ſtill to hold faſt her integrity,<note place="margin">22 <hi>Luk</hi> 31.32. 2 <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.</note> and <hi>Satans</hi> ſhaking her with his temptations, did but help to eſtabliſh her the more afterwards, and well indeed might ſhe hold faſt the integrity of her Faith, who continued to hold faſt the integrity of her Obedience, walking as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in all the Commandements and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch Conſcience of the diſcharge both of her perſonal and relative duties, that ſo farr as I have obſerved or been acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though many Daughters have done vertuouſly, yet ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled them all. The ſtrength of Faith is beſt judged of,<note place="margin">31 <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.</note> when brought to the Tryal. And I ſhall never forget her deportment under the ſad death of her moſt dear Husband.<note place="margin">Mrs. Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> When I took upon me the boldneſſe to ask her in private (her Daughter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then only preſent) whether ſhe did under this affliction doubt of Gods Fatherly love, or whether the guilt of any Sin, but thoſe which are called Sins of dayly incurſion,<note place="margin">Quotidianae incurſionis. Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> preſſing her Conſcience did render the affliction more bitter? her anſwer was, ſhe did not doubt, ſhe was aſſured of Gods love: She looked on God at that time as an angry Father, but ſhe had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found him, and then knew him to be a loving Father. And for the guilt of any Sin preſſing her Conſcience, ſhe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that her infirmities were many,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Nehem.</hi> 11. 119 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.</note> and though her deſire was to fear Gods name, and to direct her wayes according to his Statutes; Yet ſhe was defective in many things: and fell ſhort of her duty (that was her grief) of her deſire likewiſe (that was her comfort) but ſhe profeſſed that her Conſcience did not accuſe her of any wicked or willful diſobedience,<note place="margin">119 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 119 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.</note> ſhe hated every falſe way, and had reſpect unto all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements at all times:<note place="margin">79 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</note> only ſhe feared that in this affliction God might remember former iniquities long ſince committed, which, it may be, ſhe had not throughly humbled her ſelf for. I asked her then, why ſhe was ſo ſorrowful? the ſubſtance of her reply was, that ſhe thought a more than ordinary meaſure of ſorrow was in ſuch caſes lawful, being warranted out of the Scripture by the examples of good men; and alſo convenient
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39037:21"/>
to expreſs the ſenſe of Gods hand upon her; but yet ſhe deſired (ſhe ſaid) and would endeavour ſo to reſtrain her grief, that it might neither offend others, nor diſhonour God.</p>
            <p>Being thus full of the grace of faith, ſhe could not but be full of love, ſeeing faith where it is, works by love. A great lover ſhe was of the ordinances,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.</note> a lover likewiſe of Gods people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> her delight was in the Saints of the earth, in her eyes a vile perſon was contemned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16</hi> Pſal. <hi>3. 15</hi> Pſal. <hi>4.</hi> Chriſtum hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantem in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtino.</note> but ſhe honoured them that fear the Lord: where ſhe ſaw any thing of Chriſt, ſhe loved the perſon, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> loved Chriſt dwelling in <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> I think one of the greateſt arguments of a mans love to Chriſt, is, when it puts him upon endeavours to gain others to the love of him: and in this very thing ſhe ſpent moſt of her time (wherein through Gods bleſſing) ſhe laboured with ſuch ſucceſſe, that beſide her natural daughters, I doubt not but ſhe hath many other daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the faith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2.</note> who may ariſe up and call her bleſſed: ſuch whom ſhe was a ſpecial inſtrument either to beget unto Chriſt,<note place="margin">31 <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.</note> or afterwards to build up in their holy faith.</p>
            <p>She was full of the ſpirit of prayer and ſupplication; in which duty ſhe was very frequent according to the injunction of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture:<note place="margin">12 <hi>Za.</hi> 10. 4 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</note> and though ſhe was not an Euchite, ſo as to neglect all other duties of her calling, yet ſhe remembred that all things are ſanctifyed by prayer,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</note> and therefore would never omit it. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> would have men ſo much in this duty, that they might be able to ſhew the wounds of the knees,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and there is a figure in the Heavens which Aſtronomers call, in the knees. Sure I am, this Gentlewoman, if any, might have ſhewed the wounds of the knees; for ſet aſide her private and family devotions, I have ſeen her my ſelf once, twice, &amp; more than the third time in private meetings uſe this geſture for four or five houres toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and though age and her infirmities might have tolerated her another poſture, yet I have obſerved to my admiration, that for ſo long time ſhe hath ſeldome changed her geſture, when others more young and ſtrong have made uſe of their liberty to ſit or ſtand.<note place="margin">12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</note> It is not enough that we be frequent in prayer, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe fervent; no more did this ſervant of God think it. The Orator ſaid once of the <hi>Athenians</hi> (comparing them to men running up an hill) they breath much,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but have little ſtrength; ſo many men in prayer breath much, but have little ſtrength: whereas <hi>Baſil</hi> would have us with an holy impudence to make God aſhamed,<note place="margin">32 <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that he cannot look us in the face, if he deny our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39037:21"/>
importunity. Such a powerfull faculty had this Gentlewoman in prayer, as I have heard thoſe that lived with her acknowledge and admire. One thing of her practiſe in this duty, I may not omit; and that is, ſhe uſed to go to prayer with her children alwayes about five of the clock in the afternoon, and then exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined them: and becauſe ſhe was ſenſible, how much the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Church depends upon Gods guidance of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours thereof, therefore in her devotions ſhe never forgot to pray for the King, and taught her Children, while they were yet young, to do ſo.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>She was full of humility, which is the grace of all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. She would often ſay, that ſhe was the chiefeſt of Sinners.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</note> Her Eyes were ever full of her own wants; none (ſhe would ſay) enjoy'd ſuch means and mercies, and none had profited leſſe by, or walked more unworthy of them. She was ſtill jealous of herſelf, and ſuſpected that which others were ready to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud.<note place="margin">9 <hi>Ez.</hi> 13. 32 <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.</note> She thought the greateſt Evils were below her Sins, and the leaſt favours above her deſervings; The more we receive ſaid ſhe, the more we are in debt, and therefore ſhould be more humble, for will any man be proud of his debts? She was obſerved never to ſpeak of Pride, but with Vehemency of deteſtation; for ſhe would often mention a ſaying of Mr. <hi>Strong,</hi> that we are neither able to work grace, nor act grace, nor keep it in being, without a freſh ſupply from God, and therefore what had we to be proud of?<note place="margin">2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.</note> She remembred that of the Apoſtle, in lowlyneſs of mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves: and therefore was apt to admire that in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whilſt the ſame or better in her ſelf,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> ſhe thought unworthy to be mentioned. She was ever ready in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to preferre others before her ſelf and therefore would often give that reſpect to ſome, as ſuperiours, which by others were judged to be her inferiours: and though ſome judge this meanneſs of Spirit, yet they are blades of the beſt metall and making, which will bend moſt. To her inferiours ſhe was exceeding condiſcending; and when ſhe thought that ſhe had in anger ſpoken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nadviſedly, ſhe would afterwards as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge it to them. In her apparel ſhe would obſerve a grave decency: Her ordinary ſaying was, that ſhe would not be firſt in a faſhion, neither would ſhe be ſingular: Yet ſome about her obſerv'd, that ſhe never did wear a Silk Gown (though lying beſide her) ſince theſe troubleſome times; till they were hoped to draw nigh ſome Settlement. She was ever ambitious
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39037:22"/>
in ſtudying to avoid any appearance of vain glory: For this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it was (as I conjecture) that when any of her Childrens Servants happened to be at her Houſe in her Husbands abſence, ſhe was not willing that they ſhould be preſent, when ſhe went to prayer with her own Servants. Thus when ſhe ſent out her Almes (I perceive ſince her Funeral) ſhe would make choice for a Meſſenger, one that was leaſt known in the City, that it might be leſſe ſuſpected from whom they came; and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes gave the Meſſengers this charge, that they ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal who ſent the Almes, but only to ſay that a Friend ſent them. For this reaſon, when ſhe had ſet a part a day on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for private Prayer and Faſting in her Chamber alone, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Friend or Stranger came to viſit her, She bad thoſe that knew or gueſſed how ſhe was employed, not to ſay that ſhe was buſie; but to come and tell her; and ſhe would come down and give entertainment to thoſe that viſited her, and afterwards return to her Devotion. And this ſhe did (as I think) leſt it ſhould be ſuſpected, that ſhe was ſo well imployed. Her Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility appeared at her Death; in that ſhe willed (for the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of oſtentation, as much as coſt) to be buried in this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure place; when her Son offered, that he would of his proper charges, take care to have her Body removed to <hi>York,</hi> and there with Funeral Solemnity, interred in the Cathedral-Church by her Husband,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.2, 3.</note> who were lovely and pleaſant in their lives, &amp; therefore their ingenuous Heir would not have had them at their deaths divided. She ſhewed her Humility likewiſe in making choice of me by her Will to Preach at her Funeral, one indeed not able or worthy to commend a woman of ſuch vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; and whom ſhe thought knew but little of her, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not ſay much. This her avoiding of vain glory ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to be like the Silkworm, which hides it ſelf within the curious Silk it works, therefore we may upon her inſcribe the ſame Motto, that is uſually given to the Silk-worm, <hi>operitor dum operatur,</hi> ſhe is all covered, whilſt ſhe works. Let not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wonder, that a perſon ſo Holy ſhould be ſo Humble; For ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, that God gives grace to the Humble, it is no marvel, that gracious perſons are moſt Humble, and Humble perſons the moſt full of grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note>I cannot inſiſt on every particular. I paſſe from her <hi>inhoerent</hi> good works wrought in her, to her <hi>tranſient</hi> good works wrought by her. I will nor preſume ſo farr, as into her Cloſet: but her Houſe was an Houſe of Prayer, wherein the Morning &amp; the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39037:22"/>
ſacrifice were daily offered up to God, conſiſting of two ſet ſervices alwayes, prayer, and reading the word; and as occaſion would give leave, of a third, <hi>viz.</hi> ſinging a Pſalme: to theſe were added Catechizing. It is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he had three hundred trained ſervants, (or as the Original will bear it) catechized ſervants, 14 <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. ſhe had (though not ſuch a number) yet thoſe ſhe had, were catechized ſervants. One thing I have obſerved that when ſhe had any ſtrangers lodged in her houſe, ſhe took care that they had a Bible laid in their chamber; that ſo they might have proviſion for their ſoules, as well as their bodies: her care was commendable in making ſuch proviſion, if they were ſo careleſſe as not to make uſe of it, that was none of her fault.</p>
            <p>She was a ſtrict obſerver of the Lords day, and ſaw that her ſon and her daughter,<note place="margin">20 <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.</note> her man-ſervant and her maid-ſervant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it likewiſe. On this day ſhe would not lye till the ringing of the bell called her up; but, if want of health hindred not, roſe the ſooner, that ſhe might ſet her heart and houſe in order, ſo as that her ſelf and family might attend upon God with the leſſe diſtraction. Her ordinary ſaying was, if our dear Saviour roſe ſo early in the morning for the work of our redemption,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. 28 <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.</note> ſhall we think much to riſe early for his ſervice? this I took notice of and have heard her ſay, that ſhe obſerved the Lords-day always as a day of ſolemn thankſgiving; and her ſervants (though plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully fed at all times) were ſure to have a meſſe more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary that day, yet not till night, becauſe ſhe would not detain any of them from a better feaſt of the ordinances.<note place="margin">25 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>She was a moſt humble and conſtant attender upon the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word. She never went to Church, either Lords-day or other day, but firſt begged of God a bleſſing upon what ſhe ſhould hear. For the help of her memory, ſhe took notes her ſelf, and cauſed them under her to do the like; and at evening for the advantage of her family, ſhe uſed repetition: beſides ſhe ſpent three houres every Munday in reviſing of, and rumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon her own notes. She hath gone many times three miles on foot in an afternoon to ſermon, not out of novelty, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: for being forced from <hi>York</hi> in the beginning of theſe times, ſhe lived in <hi>Holdernes,</hi> where the Miniſter preached but once a day: ſhe was his auditour ſo often as he preach'd, yet could not ſatisfie her ſelf with hearing but once, as he did in preaching once; and therefore (though it was winter) ſhe would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39037:23"/>
have gone ſo far, often even on foot (I ſuppoſe for the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of her ſervants) to ſermon. I have heard her frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admire Gods great goodneſſe to this ſinfull Nation, in vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing unto it ſuch abundant proviſion both for life and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.</note> for (ſaid ſhe) brown bread with the Goſpel is good fare: and I am verily perſwaded, ſhe could have lived on the courſeſt bread, ſo ſhe might but have had the water of life with it: but however, ſhe could have been content to have lived with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, yet ſhe ever deſired that they who labour in the word and doctrine might fare well. To this purpoſe ſhe would have open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her hand wide; though a miniſter had a competency of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral eſtate, yet ſhe would ſay, that was nothing to them that lived under his miniſtry; as he laboured among them, ſo the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer was worthy of his hire,<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18.</note> not only what might be neceſſary for ſubſiſtence, but ſomething for encouragement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">19 <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.</note>She was a woman, that would not ſuffer ſin to lye upon thoſe that were her charge, for want of ſeaſonable reproof: yet ſhe alwayes tempered her reproofs with the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">6 <hi>Gal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was wiſe to obſerve the fitteſt time and place, together with the diſpoſition of the perſon, and having done this, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſucceſſe to God by prayer. If ſhe ſaw that ſhe did not reclaim one by her admonitions, as ſhe deſired, ſhe would conclude her reproof and advice with that pathetical expreſſion, well,<note place="margin">13 <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.</note> if you will not hear, my ſoul ſhall weep in ſecret places for your pride: and her ſincerity appeared in this, that ſhe was as willing others ſhould admoniſh her, and would deſire them to do it: ſhe would ſay to her daughters and others under her, it may be, you are afraid to anger me, but I pray, if you ſee any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in me, tell me of it.</p>
            <p>She was one of a very peaceable and courteous converſation: diſſention ſhe hated, and was grieved very much when any fell out in her family: if that her ſelf had taken an offence at any perſon in her houſe (though moſt juſtly) yet ſhe could not have been ſatisfied, till reconciled to them; yea, ſhe would have conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to have ſought peace of her inferiour, although ſhe had been the party that had received the injurie. She was ſometimes troubled at the ſtrangeneſs of friends, but then ſhe remembred a ſaying of Mr. <hi>Aiſcough,</hi> and would ſay, oh that I could do as he preſcribed! the ſaying was this; it may be thou art troubled for Gods peoples not loving of thee, but do thou labour to love them, and thou ſhalt never anſwer for their not loving of thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:39037:23"/>She was very frequent in meditation; when ſhe had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring with others, then ſhe uſed to go aſide, to commune with her own heart and diſcourſe with her ſelf:<note place="margin">4 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.</note> And though ſhe was alone, yet ſhe was not alone, for the Father was with her. She often would mention a Speech of Mr. <hi>Birchalls</hi> with tears;<note place="margin">16 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 32.</note> Ah Soul, if thou hadſt meditated on God more, thou hadſt loved him more.</p>
            <p>She was a woman, whoſe Speech was ſeaſoned with ſalt,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 6. 5 <hi>Eph.</hi> 29. 10 <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.21.</note> ever miniſtring ſome good to the hearers. Her Tongue was as choice ſilver, and her Lips did feed many. I have obſerved, how ready ſhe would be upon all occaſions, to adminiſter matter of gracious diſcourſe. I have condemned my ſelf and others of mine own calling for our ſluggiſhneſſe. I conſidered, that out of the abundance of the Heart, the Mourh ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Mat.</hi> 34.</note> and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that ſhe had a greater Treaſure of good things in her, than we had.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> At Meat-times ſhe would eſpecially move ſuch confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the better to ſeaſon the meat. She thought (according to the Greek ſaying) <hi>A plentiful Table to feed the Body, without good diſcourſe to feed the Mind, is little better than a Manger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was a woman of a ſound mind,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.13. 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 14. 13 <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14.</note> holding faſt the form of ſound words, and not toſſed about with every wind of Doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> indeed ſhe was ſo eſtabliſhed with grace (the beſt preſervative againſt Errours) and with <hi>Timothy</hi> ſo aſſured of the things that ſhe had learn'd, knowing of whom ſhe had learned them, that ſhe was not eaſily, removed. This may ſerve as a taſt to ſhew, how full ſhe was of good works. I proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorcas</hi> was full of Alms-deeds which ſhe did,<note place="margin">6 <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.</note> ſo was our <hi>Dorcas.</hi> How full I know not, for I believe ſhe did not let her left hand know, what her right hand did.<note place="margin">7 <hi>Mark</hi> 36.</note> But I read in the Goſpel, how Chriſt when he had cured an infirm Man, charged him that he ſhould not publiſh it, but the more he was charged to conceal it, the more did he divulge it: So I ſuppoſe, though ſhe charged thoſe, to whom ſhe gave Almes, that they ſhould not divulge it, yet they could not be kept ſecret. I have heard, that her Houſe was a little Hoſpital, not ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the poor came thither for relief, but becauſe relief went from thence for the poor: So that what <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaid of <hi>Pamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> that he was <hi>munerarius pauperum et egentium candidatus;</hi> The like may be ſaid of her, ſhe was the candidate of the Poor, as ambitious of their Prayers, as others are of their praiſes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting when ſhe had given an Almes, to have received rather
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39037:24"/>
than done a good turn, Whilſt her Husband was alive, the poor had both Food and Phyſick. And whatever he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (as his diſpoſition was well enough known) I do believe, and not upon ſlender grounds, that ſhe kept a Stock of her own, with her Husbands approbation, for the poor, and pious uſes. I have given you a brief account of the life of our <hi>Dorcas,</hi> I come now to her Sickneſſe and Death, which becauſe they were but ſhort, therefore I will not be long about them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>She was Sick and Dyed.</hi> I told you, there is a providence of God to be obſerved in the Sickneſſe and Death of his Saints; and ſo there was a remarkeable providence in the Sickneſſe and Death of this Saint, ſo well known and obſerved, that I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to mention it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it came to paſſe in thoſe days;</hi> So it is come to paſſe in theſe days, theſe calamitous and diſtracted days, wherein the Church ſtood in great need of her Prayers, that ſhe was Sick and is Dead. The times are bad already, we have cauſe to fear, becauſe of her death,<note place="margin">Cùm ſtellae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, venti ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentur. Ariſt.</note> and others like her, that they will be worſe. When ſuch Stars fall, it is a ſign of ſtorms about to ariſe. The Lord in mercy prevent them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>She was Sick and Dyed.</hi> Sickneſſe is the ſummons to Death, &amp; the time of Sickneſſe is that, which God in mercy vouchſafeth to his Children to fit them for Death. Her Sickneſs was but ſhort, therefore you may ſay, her time of preparation was not long. There was no ſuch need of it, her whole life had been a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Death, and now ſhe had little elſe to do, but to render her Soul into Gods hands. Her Diſeaſe was judged to be a Pluriſie, it began with a pain in her ſide, and ſo increaſed, It brings to my mind, that which I read of <hi>Peter,</hi> 12 <hi>Act.</hi> how the Angel ſmote him on his ſide, ſaying, ariſe up quickly, and his Chains fell off from his hands: So did the Lord ſmite her on her ſide, and her Chains of Sin and Sickneſſe, and Mortality, quickly fell off from her; And now her Soul being unpinioned, is mounted up above the Clouds till the day that ſhe ſhall come with Chriſt in the Clouds to Judgement. In her Sickneſſe I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended her very patient, yet ſhe deſired me that I would beg of God for her a greater meaſure of patience, for though the Spirit was willing, yet the fleſh (ſhe ſaid) was weak.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">26 <hi>Mat.</hi> 41.</note>
               <hi>She was Sick and Dyed.</hi> So our <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cas</hi> not inferiour to her in the Text, though ſo holy a woman, yet could not be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from paying her laſt debt to nature. Some, it may be, will
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39037:24"/>
be inquiſitive to know, how ſhe Dyed? I anſwer, firſt, though ſhe Dyed ſoon, yet not ſuddenly I perceive, ſhe hath for a long time Dyed dayly in her expectation, and hath frequently told her Friends, that ſhe might not ſtay long with them. There are many events and ſecond cauſes, that help to haſten Death, and beſide the infirmities of her Bodie, I believe the late loſſe of her moſt dear Husband, might be a means to ſhorten her dayes, Secondly, She Dyed moſt comfortably. Being asked of one about her, the Morning before ſhe Dyed, how ſhe did; She ſaid, ſhe was all peace, peace within and peace without. About two days before ſhe Dyed, when I asked her, how it was with her; Her anſwer was; Sir I am very ill, I have a great pain in my ſide, and ſpit blood: But I thank God, I have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the great Gulfe, for I am aſſured, and ſhe went over with it again (ſpeaking more heartily than at other times) Ey, I am aſſured that God hath pardoned all my ſins: and then ſhe fell into an admiration of Gods mercy to her; but (ſaid ſhe) how unworthily have I walked off, and unſutably to ſuch great love! and at the uttering of theſe words, I know not, whether ſhe did refrain her ſelf from weeping. When I farther asked her, whether ſhe did not believe, that God had pardoned this Sin to her, as well as the reſt? She anſwered, ſhe doubted it not, yet it could not but trouble her to think of it. Thus ſhe continued to her Death, for any thing I heard to the contrary. She knew (ſhe ſaid) her State was ſafe; but ſhe deſired, if God ſaw good, that he would rebuke <hi>Satan,</hi> that it might be comfortable, ſo long as ſhe lived: To this purpoſe we prayed with her ſeveral times, and it pleaſed God to grant her requeſt.</p>
            <p>So I have given you the Parallel between <hi>Dorcas</hi> and this worthy Gentlewoman deceaſed. I am ſure, I have not repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented things to you in ſuch lively colours, as they deſerved; but I have not ſet a falſe Gloſſe upon any thing. What remains, but as I have done this to excite you to follow her ſteps, ſo that I exhort you in the words of the Apoſtle, 6 <hi>Heb.</hi> 11, 12. I deſire, that every one of you would ſhew the ſame diligence, to the full aſſurance of hope, to the end; tint you be not ſlothful, but followers of them, who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
